Hey.
Hey. Hey. Heat.
Hey. Hey. Hey.
Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome to the Ask Abijit
show. Today we discuss geopolitics and
history. I'm going to take questions
that you have asked in the comments. So
before we get into the questions, let us
see who all is there on the live chat
with us tonight or today. I can see
Nirwana Shanks Kuri Chiva and and thank
you very much. Uh Namaste Pranam from
Singapore. Hello Mac 4 J1U. Sam the
gamer. Uh Soldier Boy Meow Pratam
Namaste Mahita Bushetti. Hello. Galawad
says Narendra from Tokyo. Narendra from
Tokyo. Good to have you from Toronto.
From Toronto. Well, good to have you.
Thank you so much for being on the live
stream. Swami, hello. Ombbe Kikar, good
to see you. Hello. Uh, Priyanis Sud,
hello. Good to see you. Uh, Geopolitical
Dubai, good evening. And geopolit
geopolitical Dubai is here from Indor.
Real painter says Meow Meow. Abishek
Shri Vastav. Hello. Anand Sam the gamer.
Tanesh Pande. Soldier boy. Sam the
gamer. Priyanchi Sud brute cold. Pratik
Vora, Manhattan, Soldier Boy. Adwit
Ashwini, good evening. Chatanya Manuja,
hello. Naman Dadash, namaste. Reika HL
Jri Ram Sam the Gamer Sam the Gamer
Chhatany Manuja Jimmy Lee Wand Matram
minimalist Maverick hello AJ Ra hello
Mac 4 Namaste Pram um who else do we
have Rahul Himani is from Mumbai hello
Sagar Dadani from Karnataka good to have
you Adashani
uh Aayush Singh Panam Panam Raguir is
here from Jud
Latangi Suresh from Chola Chola land.
Uh, good to have you from Chula land
indeed. Revenant Revenant Volat
an Shika Yadada. Hello. Good boys.
93931. Aayush from IIT. Gandhinagar.
Hello. Good to have you. Uh, Shivam
Chakur Web of Gupta. Priyanka Javalia.
Hello. Good evening. Rahul Himani from
Mumbai. Hello. Uh, Crazy Brain. Good to
have you. Real Radi Bhutin is back. Um
good to have you as well ready always
ready Bamshi Kalem hello it's Bamshi
Kalim good to see you again uh Krishna
of the Sury number Netherlands always
good to have you Krishna G
and everyone else I won't be able to
greet all of you individually as always
but you know Abishakupla is here from
Kpur Raguir is here from Jodpur
um Rasputin says namaste well namaste
Rasputin G Shivamakur hello and um
Amisha Krishna good evening good to have
you ma'am
Mahita Bushi says Har Krishna Har
Krishna indeed Har Krishna Zins Corner
Jind
Om omsud namaste Amir Shar hello Dea
Joti Gope
General Subutai General Subutai Anandv
hi Himank the gamer and everyone else
mlevin hello good to see you okay let's
get going with the questions what
questions do we have I will first deal
with some geopolitics questions and then
I shall deal with some history
questions. So what do we have? What are
the questions that we have? Let's get
going. Let's find let's start. Let's
begin with the questions. What do we
have? What pressing issues concern us
today? Let's see.
Aayush Singh says what is with the
recent failures of ISRO? People are
going hyper saying it was a sabotage.
What's my opinion? What are the causes
and was this really a sabotage
considering it was the the rocket was
launching military satellites?
Real brain says recent rocket failure by
ISO looks like a sabotage. First, it was
important for India's national security
as well as ISRO's international
reputation as a reliable space agency
for satellite launches. Secondly, these
type of failures by ISO are very rare.
So, what's what the rocket that failed
is ISRO's PSLV rocket. So the PSLV
rocket had a string of almost like 18 20
successful launches. It was so
successful its launches had become
boring. Everyone knew it would go
flawlessly. And then the last two
launches have failed. It's always the
same problem. Some something happens
something goes wrong at the third stage.
So let's just quickly take a look at
isro I mean the PSLV uh the way the PSLV
has been performing uh
last 20 PSLV
launches
success failure
let's see what it says
okay
so last 20 PS launches up to 2026 is
through two consecutive failures
Uh before that the PSV was incredibly
reliable. Most missions being fully
successful.
Um
the last two launches have failed. 2026
January 12 and 2025 May 18. May 18 was
the first major failure in over a
decade. Third stage third stage 21
consecutive successful flights before
this. And as you can see we are having
very few rocket launches now in India.
May 18, 2025 and then January 12, 2026
PSLV. Obviously, we have other rockets,
but as you can see, India is not
launching a lot of rockets anymore.
Um,
so yeah, we've had two consecutive
failures. Both time it's it's been a
glitch in the third stage. Now the
question is what happened? This
incredibly reliable rocket, 21
consecutive successful launches. Why
should things start going wrong with
that? Makes no sense, right? It's a
design the ISRO engineers have
perfected. It works flawlessly every
time. And now suddenly two consecutive
failures. Same uh same issue. Something
goes wrong with the third stage. Is this
sabotage? Well, look back at the past.
We've we've had issues like this. For
example, in the 1980s when the French
were developing the Aryan rocket, they
had multiple failures which was then
traced back to a to a Soviet spy, a
Soviet sabotur. And all of that is now
conveniently buried. You look for
information today, it won't show you
anything. But I've seen that I was a kid
in the 1980s that and if you're in
Europe, this this came on the news.
So you had this this sort of thing
before.
Okay. And if you remember a couple of
years ago, I had made a video about the
possibility that Chundrean too may have
been hacked and sabotaged,
right? And I had given evidence that
indicates there's the possibility
significant possibility that Chandrean 2
was actually sabotaged. It did not just
fail because of some some some you know
normal issue.
And now we have PSLV
India's most successful most reliable
workhorse rocket failing completely out
of the blue two times in succession
and each time it failed it it was it was
carrying sensitive satellites that are
important for India's national security
right
so that obviously raises the possibility
that this may have been a sabotage the
other launches were well non national
security satellite launches but this
these two the past two failures the two
consecutive failures the rocket was
carrying
satellites related connected with
India's national security military
satellites so so to say military
applications
so do I know what's happened I haven't
analyzed this in detail the government
will obviously set up an inquiry ISRO
will do an inquiry it'll put out some
kind
you know report of the inquiry possibly
in the public domain maybe not
but whatever will be put out in the
public domain it may not be the entire
story right
excuse me because of security reasons
you know some things have to be kept
classified so we in the public what can
we
um assume what happened I what I can say
is that look there are multiple issues.
First of all it is very clear now that
India is not taking the space program
seriously at all. The government of
India is essentially look treating the
space program as something that should
be kept on life support have three or
four rocket launches a year maybe five
maximum or six maximum and that's about
it.
The Chinese launch more than 100 rockets
every year. Spac X launches hundreds of
rockets every year. Spaces Space X
launches more rockets in a week than
India launches in a year
and we are not developing any major new
rocket. It's all
iterative incre incremental progress.
Why why can't India develop a rocket
that's like 10 times more powerful than
the GSLV? Why not?
Right? So um India is not taking space
seriously. India is
The government of India has decided for
whatever reason to just keep the space
program on life support. Don't do
anything ambitious. Just keep it going.
Uh funding funding is minimal.
I've been saying this for a long time
that ISRO is is is starved of funding.
ISRO is made to do missions on a
shoestring budget. I have said this
multiple times in the past few years.
I've said this on other podcasts outside
of this channel too. I've said this on
the beer biceps channel Ranir Labadia
and then Reanir interviewed Dr. Snomnath
the then head of the of the of ISRO and
Ranir asked Dr. Omnat about the
criticism I've been making that ISRO not
not the criticism but the point I've
been making that ISRO isn't it is
starved of money the budgets are very
low and he said that you know what the
budgets certain missions are
greenlighted by the government and some
money is given for that and if the and
you you the money is always obviously
limited and at the end of the year
sometimes you have to return the money
to the government so that's how it is I
mean whatever is left over in case the
in case ISRO has been successfully
extremely frugal or whatever. So
overall,
ISRO is starved of funding.
Very few rocket launches a year. If you
have a perfectly reliable rocket, you
want it you want to launch it over and
over again so that no flaws creep into
the design and the manufacturing. But if
you have a perfectly reliable rocket,
but you launch it only three times a
year, let's say, then there's a big gap
between two consecutive builds of the
rocket. And that increases the
possibility that some defects may may
creep in potentially.
So, and and people have been putting out
pictures of the workmanship on the
rocket on the PSLV rocket on on social
media. The workmanship looks shoddy. At
least the paint jobs look shoddy. Of
course, the paint job doesn't matter.
The structural integrity and other
characteristics of the rocket are more
important. But it looks like there's a
lack of pride in the way the rocket is
painted. you know, just shabily shoddily
painted and all. So, looks like the
standards aren't what you expect them to
be.
So, what do I think happened? Is it just
uh shoddy workmanship, shoddy standard,
low standards by Israel, or is it
sabotage?
If you ask me as look I don't have the
real information of what's happening
inside you know behind the scenes but
sitting over here and as someone who has
been tracking the progress of ISRO for a
long time and as somebody who has some
understanding of these things I would
say it's I would give the probability of
sabotage
at 60% or 65%. And the probability of
just a regular failure at 30 to 35%. So
I am more I I think the likelihood of a
sabotage is more than a likelihood of an
accident you know a normal accident
that's what I believe because this is
it's it's a pattern we are seeing here
and this sort of patterns have happened
before India the ISRO has been targeted
target targeted before I still believe
very strongly that there's a high
likelihood that Chundrian 2 was
sabotaged
okay some clowns were mocking me when I
put up that video at the time where are
they now
So I think there's a high likelihood
this was a sabotage. Can I prove it? No.
Because I don't have access to the to
well the inside information. The
government needs to take this very
seriously and the government needs to
take the space program very seriously
not treat it like a stepchild which is
what we are seeing right now. Okay.
Next.
Ritik P says is the $36 billion deal for
just 114 Rafals a four 4.5 generation
fighter not even fifth generation. Is
this deal really worth it or are we
making a blunder? First, we could fund
our own engine AMCA twin engine deck
based fighter the M2 etc. with the same
amount. Second, are there under the hood
factors in the deal? And that's why we
are not choosing the Sukoy 57. Look,
there are multiple aircraft that are put
out there. Okay, first of all, let's
deal with the foreign foreign aircraft.
You have the Rafa 4.5 4.5 generation
fighter. Uh then you have the Sukoy 57
which is a new fighter plane that the
Russians have developed and then there's
the F-35 that the Americans are
allegedly supposedly offering to India.
Well, which should which one should we
go for among these three? So two of
these are fifth generation fighter
planes. The the F-35 and the Suka 57 and
the Rafal is a 4 and a half generation
fighter planes. So slightly inferior.
Now when it comes to these three
aircraft, what about the uh F-35? the
F-35 it's clear India cannot buy it
India should not buy it it will be
suicidal to buy it because to to even
launch to even drop a bomb from that
from that uh fighter plane you need to
take permission from the Americans that
that fighter plane comes with all kinds
of back doors and kill switches built in
everyone knows that it just doesn't make
sense and it's just too expensive even
if it's even if you forget the expenses
you are not in sovereign control of the
asset that you paid for so there's no
point buying the F-35 anyway it's a
flying crash can like I say and it'll
make some people upset, they can go
somewhere else. Then you have the Sukoy
57. Now, why not the Sukoy 57?
The Sukoy 57 is well, it's a pretty good
fighter plane from what we hear. But
about 20 of these have been built by the
Russians so far, only 20. And they
haven't inducted the Sukoy 57 in large
numbers into their own air force, the
Russians. So, if the Russians haven't
still inducted this aircraft in large
numbers in their air force, but they are
offering to sell it to us, it raises
some questions. If it's that good, why
don't you have a few hundred of these?
Why only 20 or so? So, it's not yet the
it looks like it is still an aircraft
under development. It's not the final
version. So, typically, you know how
aircraft are designed and and and rolled
out. You design an aircraft, a mark
aircraft and you build maybe 15 20 of
those and you induct the that aircraft
into the armed forces into the air
force. They fly around, they give you
all the feedback. Then you incorporate
all the feedback with all the defects
and all the strength and all that into
the next version of the aircraft. You
build 20 more with all those
improvements baked in. Then you induct
those 20 into the air force. Then you
get more feedback from the air force as
to what can be improved. Then you do a
Mark III or version three of the
aircraft. Once version three rolls out,
it is probably the best you can have.
And then whatever improvements you made
in version three, you then retrofit
those improvements into the version one
and version two aircraft. So looks like
the Sukoy 50. That's how the worldass
air forces do it. In India, we say we
want the best aircraft from day one. You
know that that's how we do it. In India
is very different. India is a fantastic
country, isn't it? But that's how the
professional air forces do it. They roll
out aircraft in small blocks. 20 is for
for version one or mark 1, 20 more for
MK 2, 20 more for Mark 3. Then you
retrofit the the improvements for Mark
III back into MK 2 and MK1. Then you do
a MarkV or you start a new family of air
of aircraft. Or maybe you then produced
100 or 200 of Mark III. That's how you
do it in a professional air force. So
even if whatever requirements you have
mark 1 only meets 70% of the
requirements you still induct that into
the air force so that you can get large
quantities of data from the from the
from the flying hours. That's how it's
done. So the Suka 57 looks like it's the
Mark 1 or the version one of the
aircraft. Maybe they're going to improve
it over time
and it's not the final version yet.
So because the Russians have only
inducted about 20 of the Zuko 57 in
their air force, maybe we it's too early
to buy that. Now the Rafal, why the
Rafal?
We already have 36 Rafal, right? We know
how to use the use the goddamn bird. We
know how to use it. Then it's a pretty
well, if we are buying more, it means
that it's a good one. It's it's a good
aircraft. Uh so buy a bunch more. See,
we don't want to have a zoo, a menagery
of 53 different kinds of aircraft. It's
a nightmare, logistical nightmare to get
the spares to have the technicians
trained into in all the different
classes of aircraft. You should have two
or three kinds of aircraft at most,
right? We have the Jaguar, we have the
Mirage, we have the Sukoy 30, we have
the Mig 29, we have the MiG 21, we have
the TJ Mark 1A, then we have the Rafal.
I mean, it's already a six seven
aircraft right there. It's already a
nightmare.
Okay, if you get a Sukoy, it's it's part
of the same class of birds as a Sukoy
30. So much of the infrastructure you've
built for the Sukoy 30 can be reused,
repurposed for the Suka 57, I'm sure.
But that's the issue with the Suka 57.
They've only injected 20 the Russians,
which is an which is an issue. So, so
because we already have the Rafal, it's
performed well apparently from whatever
we hear. That's why the government said
okay, let's go for the Rafal and it's
the deal isn't finalized yet. this this
the all the Indian media whatever it's
reporting that we are paying these many
thousand cr rupees or whatever the deal
hasn't been finalized
we haven't inked any agreement yet okay
and whatever the final deal is it's
going to include all the all the all the
weapons systems all the missiles and god
knows what else apparently the French
are saying that we will not give you
access to the source code etc so there's
a lot of more negotiations that need to
be done we need to have access to the
mission computers So that if we
integrate new weapons, Indian weapons
into the system then they should be well
there should be fully integraable into
the system into the aircraft. So there's
a lot more negoti negotiating to be done
and looks like because we are going for
the SAF engine that the French uh that
we are co-developing with the French
that's why maybe it makes sense for the
Rafal to go for the Rafal and of course
you are absolutely right with all this
money that we are spending on the Rafals
we can fund our own engine but the
government for whatever good reason or
bad reason I'm not sure we have once
again decided to put the cavary engine
on the back burner and over all these
years and decades that we have been
developing the cavary engine we've spent
peanuts on the engine. Peanuts. We don't
fund our development of our own
technology. We want to buy foreign
technology, right? We have spent peanuts
over maybe a billion billion and a half
dollars over the development of the
cover engine over all these decades
and then we expect it to work. So a lot
of the fault lies with the government of
India. A lot of it. Maybe some of the
blame has to be shared by the armed
forces or whatever. We don't know. or
the twin engine deck based fighter has
been put on ice right now. I don't think
it's going to happen. They just mark 2.
We'll see what it what happens with
that. It'll become operational. It will
start flying in sometime in the 2030s
maybe 5 10 years more
and even the Rafal this extra 114
whenever they come in they'll come in by
2030 or whatever. So we are going
backwards and backwards in terms of the
number of aircraft we need to have.
Ideally we should have a thousand plus
fighter planes. I mean an economy as big
as India, we are almost at parity with
Pakistan. What is the government doing?
How can a third rate nation like
Pakistan have almost near parity with
India in terms of the numbers of fighter
planes? What kind of a joke is this?
The government clearly has a lot of lot
to answer.
I mean this government is in power has
been in power how many years? 11 plus
years almost 12 now. What have they
done? So yeah, so um that's where we
are. But the the main answer to your
question is that we still haven't
finalized the Rafal deal. It's still not
finalized. And should we, you know, go
for a production line of the Sukoya 57?
Well, if the Suko 57 is indeed a good
aircraft, then it makes sense to also
have a production line of the Suka 57 in
India. So one of the one of the
conditions we will make for the Rafal is
that the Rafal has to be produced in
India and and all the components also
need to be produced in India. It's not
just just that we should assemble the
aircraft in India. It has all the spare
parts, components, most of them should
be produced in India, manufactured in
India themselves. So these are the some
of the negotiating points we need to
finalize. The French will try to have to
maximize their interest in whatever they
get out of it. But if we are paying so
much, we need to uh you know have a much
better deal than whatever the Indian
media outlets are reporting right now.
So it's still a work in progress. These
things are interminable.
I don't know why defense acquis
acquisition in India is so such a
protracted lengthy interminable process.
I don't get it why bureaucracy right and
other I suppose allegedly other interest
and what not but what who suffers the
nation suffers as a consequence.
Uh yeah so all this money we are send
you know we we are spending and we are
paying foreigners
you know even even onetenth of that
money if we had spent on the on the jet
engine indigenous jet engine we would
have had far better results by now I
don't know what the government of India
is doing and why we are doing this but
that's where we are and it's
disappointing
real Vladimir Putin says the US has
banned number one Pakistanis and
superpower Bangladesh from entering the
US is it a way to humiliate its vasa
Rushabare says Trump has recently
suspended visas for many countries which
includes Russia, Iran, Afghanistan,
Pakistan, Bangladesh etc. Even Nepal,
even Thailand if I'm mistaken. Okay. So
we can understand Russia and Iran but
why Pakistan? Why Bangladesh? What's
really the reason the US state
department is doing this despite their
increasing partnership with the with
Pakistan and Bangladesh? Look their
partnership partnership with Pakistan
and Bangladesh is that of a master with
its was okay
that's the that's the relationship it's
the patron those guys are its clients
and they are essentially attack dogs for
the US and the Indian subcontinent and
their job is to
is is to is to be part of the US
strategy of containing India. So
Pakistan acts as
an enabler of nuclear blackmail against
India as a terrorist nation that can
strike India from time to time and keep
India off balance and so on. That's the
role of Pakistan and Bangladesh it's
another nuisance that they've created as
East Pakistan in the west in the eastern
part of India you know off the eastern
border of India. So that's the deal. So
that is the utility these two countries
have for the Americans and they pay them
well for that. So they pay the Pakistani
armed forces their their their fellow
that guy and I'm sure they're paying the
Muhammad whatever money or whatever. So
that they'll take care of their minions.
They will take care of their puppets
very well. But the Americans don't care
about the people of Pakistan or
Bangladesh, right? So why should they
issue visas to them? What the Americans
have done now, what the US government
has done now is they have suspended or
stopped visa processing for a large
number of countries, maybe more than 70
countries. Let's let's find out exactly
what the number is.
How many nations
visa processing has been suspend
suspended by the US?
Okay. 75 countries. Okay. All right. So
suspension of immigrant visa processing
for 75 countries and so so it's 75
nations right and
so why have have the Americans done
this? The Americans especially the Trump
administration they are concerned about
immigration they you know their their
voter base is concerned about American
jobs going to foreigners. They're
concerned about all these things. Um and
it's well known that many of these
countries the immigrants who come in
from these countries the immigrants
actually are a burden on the American
taxpayer. No question about that.
So if an immigrant comes in from let's
say Somalia or Sudan or Afghanistan,
Pakistan whatever or Bangladesh they
typically are a burden on the US
taxpayer over 10 years. they they they
leech money out of the system rather
than than contribute money to the system
or contribute value to the system.
If you have an Indian immigrant goes to
who goes to the US, the Indian immigrant
typically outperforms all other
immigrants in the value they contribute
to the US economy over a period of 10 20
whatever years. So the US government has
decided to suspend visa processing for
nations
that are dangerous,
potential terrorist nations or nations
that whose immigrants
are typically you know lowquality
immigrants who actually are a burden on
the US economic system and the US
taxpayer. That's what the Americans are
doing. The Indian immigrant is a net
contributor is the highest net
contributor
per capita to the US economy. Why will
the stop why will they stop processing
Indian visas? The Indian immigrant is
the highest value immigrant to the US.
So they won't do that for for India.
What about Pakistan? The Pakistani
immigrant is a burden to the US economy.
The Bangladeshi immigrant is a burden to
the US economy.
I don't know Nepal also is part of the
list apparently. Even Thailand seems to
be part of the list. I'm not sure why
but whatever. So there must be different
cons considerations for different
countries. Some countries are clearly
nations that whose whose immigrants are
burdens on the on the US system those
immigrants I mean those countries that
the visa processing if it's stopped it
just makes sense. Some other countries
maybe there are some political reasons
or whatever. We can understand Russia
political reasons. Iran political
reasons. I'm not sure if Iranian
immigrants are really on average
highquality net contributors to the US
system or economy but there could be
political reasons as well. So the
Pakistani and Bangladeshi immigrants I
mean look at the way the Pakist the the
the the the
contributions of Pakistani immigrants to
the UK
what kind of gangs grooming gangs and
whatnot that's what the Pakistanis
contribute who wants such people right
so that it's not about humiliating the
vasals or whatever it's just the it's
just that the US wants high quality
immigration and Pakistan is not that
Bangladesh is not that Somalia is not
that and so on about other countries
that's the reason
okay two questions here says if the US
attacks Iran can Iran stand up to the
might of the US military also apart from
attacking US bases in west Asia region
does Iran possess the military might to
choke hormmo
says could we talk about Iran while the
people are protesting there seems to be
no leadership inside Iran
Really? Okay. The IRGC despite being
compromised has conducted brutal
crackdowns. Really? Because the Western
media is reporting that. Is that so? Is
that why you're saying that the Iranians
blocked Starling with the help of
Russia? If the US and Israel go there,
Kami will make it a patriotic war and
the mission fails. Also, Iran is not a
rollover. They are pretty capable and
may inflict damage and fight a war of
attrition which Trump can't afford.
Trump can't afford to get bogged down in
Iran. At most, they may bomb the Iran
and nuclear facilities. So what is going
to be the endgame in Iran? Will it be a
brutal crackdown, civil war or any other
hidden moves or are we underrating them?
Okay, first of all, what Okay, first of
all, there seems to be no leadership
inside Iran. I'm not sure what's the
basis for that kind of statement or
claim. There is clear leadership within
Iran. The government is functioning.
The nation is
is being governed administered
right there is leadership clear
leadership. Uh the IRGC despite being
compromised has conducted brutal
crackdowns. How do we know they have
conducted brutal brutal crackdowns?
Because the western media is reporting
that on what basis is the western media
putting out whatever numbers 12,000
dead. On what basis? Do they have
reporters on the ground who can actually
corroborate those numbers? They don't.
So from where do these numbers of 12,000
dead come? There are some videos on
social media of some uh protests
happening over a over a period of maybe
a week or so in large cities like Thran
and Mashad perhaps etc.
That's a couple of cities maybe four
five large cities. What about the rest
of Persia? What about that? All the
hundreds of towns, villages, thousands
of villages. What about that? What about
the other provinces? What's happening
there? Nothing's happening there as far
as we can know or see. So a few cities
there are demonstrations happening over
a period of let's say 5 to 7 days or
whatever the period of time is. That
doesn't mean that Iran is under chaos.
Now brutal crackdowns. How do we know
the IRGC has been doing all this? We can
see some videos on social media of
various of some men firing
rifles or weapons at a crowd. The men
aren't wearing uniforms. They could be
IRGC in plain clothes. could be maybe
agents of some foreign country in plain
clothes. How do we know who they are? I
mean, we have to we whatever claims we
make, there has to be clear evidence for
the claim. We can't just assume it's
this or that.
So, I have no evidence the IRGC has
conducted brutal crackdowns. I have seen
some sad, terrible, tragic images of
dead people, but it's not 12,000. And I
don't know who killed them. Whether it's
the IRGC or whether it is foreign
foreign agents, I don't know who killed
them. So how do you know who killed
them? Because the BBC is saying it. Do
you trust the BBC? Have you seen BBC's
reporting towards India? All lies. Have
you seen the CNN's reporting towards
India about India? If you look at the
BBC and the CNN and all the Western
media outlets, the overwhelming majority
of its reporting about India is
negative. It's consistently negative.
Much of it is just lies. So, how can you
trust that media? I just don't get it. I
don't get why Indians don't think.
Okay. And there is the thing about
Starlink. Well, it looks like the
Iranians are successfully at least
partially successfully blocking Starlink
perhaps with Russia's aid possibly.
Okay. Now,
now the question is if the US attacks
Iran, can Iran stand up to the might of
the US military and uh
can they
can they blockade the straight of Horos?
Can they attack American bases in West
Asia, etc. So, let's take a look at the
US bases in West Asia. Okay, US bases in
Middle East. Okay, we call it they call
it Middle East, we call it West Asia.
Whatever. Here we have it. So, so as you
can see, how about this? This is
cleaner. US military facilities
facilities
in
in the Middle East. Uh let me open this
in a
different
let me let me reopen that properly.
Okay. So here's a bunch of American
military facilities in West Asia. You
have bases in Oman. You have bases in
UAE, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Iraq
obviously is under well essentially
under US occupation in Jordan. Syria is
also a US asset now. Turkey also Israel
is obviously Israel the US number one
supporter ally and of course Pakistan is
now you could say a US asset. So Iran is
kind of encircled from three directions,
right? That's where we have it. Now what
that means is that if there's a war, if
there's a US or Israeli or US Israeli
joint invasion
uh of Iran
or
or or an attack on Iran, then what you
will have is that Iran will be in a
position to strike at all these American
assets whether it's Oman, whether it's
UAE, Katar, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Iraq,
Syria, Jordan, Turkey, wherever the Iraq
Iranians can strike at these these
American uh assets
uh because the Iranians have very high
quality missiles in very large
quantities. Quality plus quantity both,
right? The Iranians could hit Israel.
They could hit all these American air
bases around them. They could hit
Pakistan if required. They could even
hit Turkey if required with their
ballistic and cruise missiles and so on.
They also have high quality drones, the
Iranians. So they could use the drones
and missiles to also blockade the
straight of Hormuz.
They also have a decent decentish navy.
But the real strength is the the
missiles that Iran has.
So Iran could be pretty capable at doing
this. Yeah. And if the US and the and
Israel attempt an invasion of Iran that
they'll get bogged down potentially
because look I don't know how many
Iranians actually are opponents of the
regime of the ayatas. I don't know
the Iranian diaspora in the west
it is overwhelmingly anti anti
the Iranian regime. They are against the
Iranian regime most of them but they
don't represent the true voices of the
people who live in Iran right the
Iranian diaspora outside Iran. So u it's
highly possible that maybe even today
maybe 55% of Iranians support the regime
maybe 65% support the regime and what
you see is just on in a couple of cities
and if Iran comes under foreign invasion
okay and US style invasions always cause
always cause large numbers of civilian
casualties. Look at the way the
Americans have done in the things in the
past. They essentially flattened Iraq in
2003.
Flattened entire cities. Obviously,
cities have people inside. We don't talk
about them, right? When the Americans
invade, they flattened cities. This
causes tremendous numbers of casualties.
The Americans say it's okay. It's part
of the game.
If Iranians are killed in this manner,
do you think even the ones who support
who are against the regime, you don't
think they'll fight back? Iran's a
pretty big country. So, um, Iran can
inflict damage. Iran can fight. Of
course, um, pinpoint strikes. It's
something the Americans are very capable
of. They can take out nuclear
facilities, military facilities. I'm
sure if the Americans quickly take out
the the missile facilities, then Iran
could be kind of a sitting duck, but the
people will fight potentially, right?
Uh, so then overall with this
understood,
what's the endgame in Iran? That is the
big question.
What is America's endgame in Iran? What
the Americans seek
is first of all a complete end to Iran's
nuclear program. Complete end of end of
the program. And secondly, the Americans
seek control of Iran's oil and gas
resources.
They seek control over that.
Two things only. The regime change may
not even that be that important as long
as the Americans are convinced that the
Iran's nuclear program is finished. and
two the Americans can control all of
Iran's
resources of oil and gas then the
Americans are fine. So if the regime of
the Ayat
can prove provide evidence to the US
that they have completely ended the
missile the the the nuclear program and
they hand over control of oil and gas to
the Americans then the Americans will be
very pleased and they'll be that is the
end game essentially. So whatever the US
is doing globally, it's about control of
land and oil resources, energy
resources. That's what it is. And I
don't think it's going to be very easy
for the Americans to affect a regime
change in Iran. It's going to be
difficult. It's going to be chaotic if
they try it.
So
that's the situation.
So the endgame once again to reiterate
the Americans seek to control energy and
territory and resources other natural
resources critical minerals and what
not. That's what they see. They don't
care about the people of Iran or
whatever. And if you if you are if you
are under the impression that if there
is a regime change in Iran then Iran
will become a Zoroastran nation. Think
again. If the Americans actually succeed
in affecting a regime change in Iran,
they will flood Iran with Christian
missionaries. It's the first thing
they'll do. Remember that if Iran falls
to the US, Iran is not going to become a
Zoastran nation. It's going to become a
Christian nation.
Okay. Rushup T says India has issued an
advisory for our citizens to leave Iran.
Also, we see the USS Abraham Lincoln
moving from the Pacific to close to
Iranian waters. While a war may be
unlikely, we can see movement and
preparation for any eventuality. How
will instability in Iran impact India
with respect to Chabahar in the
international north south transport
transit transport corridor? How is it
impact Afghanistan? And what impact does
it have on the US on on on on Armenia
and its survival the survival of
Armenia? How will Russia and China
standings be impacted? They block
selling etc. Okay. Okay. 73 different
questions. Let's focus on one thing.
There's lots of questions embedded in
this. Let's focus on one thing.
Chabahar. What's the impact on Chabahar?
So what's happened with Chabahar? India
has liquidated its its ownership of
Chabahar. given the money to Iran, given
it back.
So Iran, India no longer owns whatever
it owned of Chabahar. India has given it
back to Iran. India has given the money
to Iran. India may perhaps still operate
some part of Chabahar.
But
that's about it. That may also end soon.
So what has India done? India has so the
Americans had given a deadline of
whatever date it's about to expire now
for the reimposition of sanctions on
Chabahar and they also have this uh 25%
additional tariffs for anybody who does
business with Iran so what has India
done India has caved into the U
India has caved into the US
India has come under US pressure and
buckled caved H
is it terrible? No, it's a practical
decision.
You see, so that's what's happened.
So look, India has been saying for a
long time, right? Whatever decisions we
make, we don't allow a third parties to
influence those those decisions.
That's not the case anymore. The US has
told us how we should behave with
respect to Iran and we have accepted
whatever the Americans have said have
said.
So now we can see what hard power is and
what soft power is. India's power is
mainly soft power.
India's hard power is this. US hard
power is that. So the Americans told
India ultimatum
get stop operating with stop doing
business with Iran. we're going to
sanction Chabahar. If you still keep
doing business with Iran, we're going to
impose 25% more tariffs on you. So,
India said, "Okay, we are out of Iran.
That's it." U is it a failure by the
government of India? No. It is a
reasonable, practical, pragmatic step.
Right? There's no comparison between
India and the US. Whatever the Americans
say, we will do it. Does this mean that
we are on on the road towards becoming a
vasal? Not exactly. It doesn't exactly
mean that. But this could be the
beginning of such a road of India
becoming an American basal. This could
be the beginning if we are not very
careful. Right? So that's where we are
right now. India has caved into the
American pressure. Visav Chabahar. So
Chabahar it's over now. essentially if
we can still operate it, it will only be
I mean see the Iranians also understand
this that India had no choice and the
Iranians also have taken actions in the
past that have been not very good for
India for example their supreme leader
keeps on talking about Kashmir from time
to time kind of supporting Pakistan so
it's not like we owe something a debt of
gratitude or something to Iran we were
working on mutually beneficial terms and
now the Americans have stepped in and
pushed India out elbowed India out and
India is
India is a lightweight compared to the
US. Please understand that okay we live
in the real world. I am not one of those
one of those people who will say oh we
are superpower we are vushwaguru we are
not. Past four years I've been saying we
are nothing like that and now you can
see the actual evidence that whatever I
have been saying is absolutely correct.
India has to be very careful. Now
the past 10 years India has been has
been doing the opposite of hide your
hide your strength and b your time. Deng
shaing said when he was alive about
China that China needs to hide its
strength and b its time. Keep quiet and
keep your doing keep doing your work
quietly. The past 10 years India has
been doing the opposite of that.
So now you see what what happens as a
consequence.
India has been shouting superpower and
wish for guru for the past 10 years
without actually do putting in the work
sufficient work to make that happen
where are the reforms where is
everything so yeah that's where we are
right now
brianka biswas says is there a
possibility for direct military
confrontation between US and NATO troops
in Greenland France is sending troops
there France is sending 15 soldiers to
Greenland the UK is sending two soldiers
Denmark is sending 78 dogs to Greenland.
And is Russia send
is Russia sending something? Look, there
is no possibility for a direct military
confrontation between the US and NATO
troops in Greenland. Zero. Zero.
Because NATO
is mostly US. The US owns NATO.
The US controls NATO. How can you go to
war with an organization you control? It
won't happen. The US, the the European
politicians,
they are all in America's pockets.
They're all in America's pockets. They
won't dare go against their master and
finance. Nothing like this will happen.
They'll make some noises and some sounds
blah blah. We oppose this etc. We are
strongly opposed to this. Maybe Mu
France will make stronger statements.
Maybe he may send instead of 28 soldiers
300 soldiers. Sir,
what difference does it make? Even
France can't actually
seriously think of fighting the US. So
this is
nothing's going to come out of this. The
Americans are going to acquire
Greenland. They're going to make a
payment. The Americans are going to make
a payment to Denmark and then formally
take over Greenland. That's what's going
to happen. This is my prediction. I
don't make predictions, but here is one.
The Americans are going to make a
payment to Denmark and then a next
Greenland. That's what the Americans
will do very soon. Very soon. How soon?
Maybe one week, maybe 3 months.
Definitely in this year, 2026.
Okay. So there's no possibility of a
direct military confrontation between
the US and NATO. No.
Um okay.
Rushabare says what's happening in
Venezuela. Nicolas Maduro is in US
custody. Moreover, Madame Madili, no
that other lady Machado, the the Nobel
Prize winning vampire. That lady, she
met Trump and gave her Nobel Prize to
Trump and then tried to satisfy Trump.
go well she gave her Nobel Prize to
Trump as as as as
tribute to Trump and uh to plate his ego
right moreover however Deli Rodriguez
and the military seem ready to cooperate
and the US has no issues will the US be
really able to extract oil from
Venezuela and profit from it and have
they started moving in this direction
and how do you see this new game of not
changing the entire regime but aligning
the regime in a way that supports your
interest how is this game okay what's
happening So they'll see. So this lady
Machado, Machado, the Nobel Prize
winner, she went to the White House and
she presented her Nobel Prize medal to
Trump and she bowed down to him and
maybe maybe she kissed her kissed his
feet or something. Whatever she did, she
seeks to rule Venezuela.
Okay, she has been saying this for a
very long time. The moment I become we
we will the moment I come to power, I
will I will hand over the whole of
Venezuela. All its industries,
everything to the US, we will make it
very easy for American companies to
operate in Venezuela. You come and take
our resources, extract everything,
plunder, pillage, kill, whatever you
want, it's all yours. That's what she's
been saying. This lady is a vampire.
She's a blood sucking ghoul. That's what
this machado lady is. I mean, the Nobel
Prize has zero legitimate legitimacy
now. zero credibility after someone like
her getting it and the Nobel committee
has made it very clear that the Nobel
Prize cannot be transferred to someone
and it can't be revoked and yet she has
attempted to transfer it to Trump and
Trump is pleased. Yes, he's pleased,
isn't he? So that's the deal with this
lady Machado. But Delilci Rodriguez who
was the vice president of Venezuela
under the presidency of Nicolas Maduro
he now is the ruler of I mean she
governs Venezuela now and the military
is aligned with her
right and she has indicated that she's
willing to cooperate with the United
States. Now what does the US seek in
Venezuela? The US seeks complete control
over Venezuela's natural resources,
energy resources. Venezuela has plenty
of gold, but more than that, it has
plenty of oil. 20% roughly, roughly 20%
of the world's proven oil resources,
reserves. This oil is extra heavy oil.
It's sour crude oil. It's not sweet,
light crude.
Very difficult to process.
What do you do with sour extra heavy
crude? You may pro you may turn it into
diesel or you may turn turn it into
asphalt.
And only three or four refineries across
the world have the capability to process
this kind of crude oil. One of these is
in India, western India, Gujarat. So uh
the US wants to control all of this oil.
It's about controlling the energy that
flows out of Venezuela. and Deli
Rodriguez I mean she's a practical
person obviously she saw what was done
to Mr. Maduro. So she says, "Okay, since
we can't do a thing about you being a
thousand times more powerful than us, we
will cooperate with you." And the US is
fine with that. And yet Trump has not
been able to thus far pursue American
oil companies to invest in Venezuela and
start operations there because the
American companies are wondering and
they're worried that maybe in the future
Venezuela may once again nationalize the
oil industry. So thus far, American
companies have been reluctant to move
into Venezuela. But you have Venezuelan
refineries and whatnot, or at least
extractors, not refineries. Not I don't
think Venezuela has refineries, but
Venezuela has the ability to extract oil
from the ground
and and the US wants to control that.
So, as long as Dil Rodriguez and the
military cooperate with the US, the US
is fine with that. The US doesn't want
to do the hard work of installing a new
regime.
Why do that when the existing regime is
cooperating? Why do the hard work of
installing an absolutely brand new
regime and setting up a whole system of
governance and law and order and
judiciary and whatnot? Why do that? Who
cares what happens to Venezuela as long
as you get the oil?
So the US has no issues as long as
they'll see and the government of
Venezuela cooperate and they are
cooperating right.
This is a win-win situation for the US
actually. They don't have to do any hard
work in Venezuela. They don't have to
install a new government and all that.
The existing regime cooperates. That is
the best outcome the US could have hoped
for. What's the alternative? The US has
to go in, fight the military, uh depose
the regime, effect an actual physical
regime change, fight the insurgency that
may erupt as a as a consequence, plead
the people, suppress the people, a lot
of effort, energy, money, expenditure,
all kinds of things.
and then you barely control the country
and then you can extract stuff out of
it. That's a lot. It's a mess. Why do
that? Just force the existing regime to
cooperate. That's it. You get everything
you want. So that is what's happening.
And the US is going to control all the
all the energy resources of Venezuela.
Right? It's part of their overall game
plan of controlling as much of the
energy supply of the world as possible
in order to isolate nations like China
and Russia. Russia won't work but China
for sure and to put immense pressure on
nations like India.
Okay, that's a game.
It's it's Sam says among the world's top
powers most have either dominant
manufacturing or dominant military tech
ecosystems. Is India trying to rise with
an asymmetric foundation and if so
where does that make us vulnerable?
So India
so you see to be a major power to be a
serious contender
geopolitically
any nation that's a serious contender or
a ser serious player
has a
has a powerful technological base and a
powerful manufacturing base. So if you
have a highquality high-tech
technological ecosystem in your country
then you can develop and design the
technologies you need to be relevant
geopolitically from a military
perspective from an economic perspective
and it's not enough to have a high
quality technological ecosystem. You
need to have a major manufacturing base
that can turn the technological
innovations into products that can be
manufactured at scale. So you need a
research and development ecosystem which
is the tech ecosystem
which could be either in your
universities or in your corporations or
in both. And then all the out all the
all the output of that needs to go into
your manufacturing
um base which will then massproduce the
products that the the advanced products
that come out of the that that
incorporate the technologies you're
developing. And that's how you become a
relevant genuinely relevant player
economically and militarily and
geopolitically.
So China is a great example of that. The
US used to be a great example of that.
The US has the world's best education
system that's focused on science and
technology and research and development.
And all of those highquality u students
that are output by the education system
are are absorbed by the industries. The
industries and corporations have their
own R&D setups everywhere and they use
these R&D setups with this fresh with
this with this bright young minds coming
from the education system to produce the
world's best products right or to design
the best products which are then either
manufactured in the US or in China. The
Chinese have copied the US setup. They
now have a worldclass univers university
system world-class education system
focused on science, technology, research
and development. And the Chinese are
also they also have these major
corporations and and they're the world's
largest
manufacturing base, industrial base,
right? Two great examples. Where does
India stand in this? India has a rotten
education system. Third grade education
system that destroys India's best minds.
India doesn't have any real R&D
happening anywhere in any university or
any IIT or whatever. Nothing. nothing of
any global value. Not even 1% of global
value comes from here.
Then India doesn't have corporations
that do R&D. Recently, Reliance, which
is a huge corporation, was seeking to
buy some technology from a Chinese
corporation, which was like a 100th of
the strength of Reliance. The Chinese
refused and Reliance now can't do what
it wanted to do because Reliance has
never bothered to invest in its own R&D.
Reliance doesn't do R&D. Reliance
manufactures. So it wanted Chinese
technology. The Chinese little company
said no. Reliance can't do a thing about
it. This is the mindset in India. So
India's education system is third grade.
It's rotten. India's uh corporations
don't do R&D.
They want to do you know screwdriver
stuff. and uh
and we don't manufacture anything that's
globally relevant textiles.
I'm talking about high-tech stuff. So
without
a world-class education system that
supplies a world-class R&D ecosystem
that supplies a world-class
industrial manufacturing base,
you are not a serious
geopolitical player. You're not
India is regarded as a as as a major
geopolitical player because of its large
economy, the fourth largest economy in
the world, big market and all. India has
a decent military. India has a
world-class missile program and so on.
But India has major major deficiencies
which need deep reforms and massive
reforms. And none of those reforms are
happening. So I'm not sure what India's
future is.
It makes us super vulnerable everywhere.
India is not taken seriously actually by
the Chinese or the Americans. The
Chinese don't see India as a contender
for
for you know the top crown. The
Americans don't see India as a contender
for the top crown. They don't take India
seriously. The Chinese don't do.
India is like Africa. It's like Nigeria
or something. Slightly better version.
Yeah, that is the truth. I'm sure you
want to hear something else but I can't
tell you lies. That's the truth.
Aish ready says namaste. Yours live
streams are like therapy to me. I keep
hearing them in loop since 2021. Thank
you very much sirishi. Thank you. The
questions are one is China more
vulnerable due to internal structural
pressures like demog demographics debt
legitimacy then to external military
pressure and does the west misread this
balance? So what is China more
vulnerable to internal pressures like
demographic decline uh lower lowering
lower you know uh dropping TFR etc.
Maybe debt I don't know what the debt
structure in China is. Um the western
media reports all kinds of weird stuff
about China that China is deeply in debt
to itself or whatever but I don't know
about that legitimacy. The Chinese
Communist Party is fully legitimate. No
Chinese citizen doubts or questions the
legitimacy of the Chinese Communist
Party to rule. The Chinese Communist
Party does have the mandate of heaven
right now. So
these are the factors that are internal
in nature. Is China vulnerable to these
pressures. Uh the demographics will kick
in as a problem in the next 20 years.
Not right now. So right now it's not an
issue. Debt I think the Chinese have the
e economy under control. Debt whatever
legitimacy. There's no question about
the legitimacy of the CCP. So there is
no such issue. So the internal
structural pressures aren't really
genuine pressures. Uh external pressure
like the military pressure.
Well, what really constrains China is
that it is extremely risk averse. The
Chinese Communist Party is very happy to
bully weaker nations. The Chinese are
extremely reluctant to go to war with
with a more powerful nation, especially
the US. The Chinese don't want a war
with the US. The US is willing to ride
rough rod everywhere. It'll go and
regime change Venezuela. They may do a
regime or at least attempt a regime
change in Iran. They have done regime
changes all over all over the place
recently in in the subcontinent, east
and west Pakistan. The Americans do all
this. They they will fire weapons.
They'll will they'll fire shots. The
Americans aren't afraid of a fight, a
military fight. The Chinese are
frightened of a military fight.
The Chinese know that if they go to war
with the US, whether they win or lose,
they will lose half of their economy at
least. Whatever they've worked for all
these years, they will lose and it's
very hard to hit the US. So that's the
major Chinese vulnerability. The Chinese
want to fight the US, but economically,
never militarily.
And that is a huge drawback of China.
And Trump knows that and is pressuring
China on that front. Right? So, China
did not want Venezuela to fall.
Venezuela fell. China did not want Syria
to fall. Syria fell. Now, who knows what
will happen in in Iran. China wants to
take Taiwan, but is frightened to take
military action. It's very clear what
China is afraid of now. It's becoming
more and more clear. China doesn't want
military action. China wants economic
warfare, but never military warfare.
The Americans know it. So they're going
to push, push, push. So that is what
China is vulnerable to. External
military pressure, not a internal
structural pressures. Second question
is strategic autonomy a coherent
long-term grand strategy for middle
powers in periods of intense great power
competition or or does historical
evidence suggest that such such
strategies collapse under systemic
crisis forcing alignment despite prior
hedging. Okay.
So historically what do we have? Let's
say you are not a very major power.
Okay. Middle power or whatever you want
to call it. You have maybe two great
powers or superpowers and those two are
are competing for you know control of
the world order and you are a smaller
nation or a weaker nation maybe large
geographically but you're weak. You're
weak. So what do you do? So ideally as a
weaker nation what you do is you play a
balancing game. You do the balancing act
the tightroppe walking act right? You
play one side against another. You try
to be friendly with both or you try to
be in such a such a position that both
want you to do something for them or
both want you on their side.
So that's the balancing game. That's the
that's what you call hedging, right? Uh
strategic autonomy.
Now that's the game India is playing
visa with the US and China.
China is more powerful than India. No
question. about four times more powerful
than India. The US is about 20 times
more powerful than India.
So that's the game we are playing. You
know, we made we became part of the
Quad.
So if you're part of the Quad, maybe the
US will assist us if there's a war with
China.
All that stuff. We bought American
weapons. We are also buying Russian
weapons and so on. We allowed American
tech products to infiltrate and
penetrate India all over the place.
Today India can't run without American
tech products, right?
Everything Indians do take for granted
whether it is Google, whether it is
Gmail, whether it is Instagram, YouTube,
Twitter, this that, WhatsApp, uh, Apple
phones, Android phones, laptops,
everything is American. What does India
make nothing? Why? Ask yourselves, what
is the government of India doing? What
have they done? Why, why does India make
nothing? But India makes nothing. So
India
became more and more tightly bound to
the US consciously voluntarily. We buy
American F4145 jet engines which are
never delivered. Did the government not
foresee that? I suppose they did not.
So that's the game of hedging. We we buy
weapons from Russia. We do trade with
China. We buy something from France. But
we do a lot of our business with the US.
So that's the kind of balancing game
India has been playing. But when push
comes to shove,
then the US says get out of Chabahar
or else India has to get out of
Chavahar. Tomorrow the US will say
something else. What will India do?
Tomorrow the US says agree to the trade
deal on our terms or we impose 500%
tariffs.
Your choice. What does India do then?
So the so when a nation is way more
powerful than you, this hedging and this
balancing doesn't work long term. It
works short term.
It worked as long as uh the US did not
feel that we need to rearrange the
entire global world world order and and
break down the rules-based world order.
So until the Biden regime, the US was
okay, let the let the so-called
rules-based world order be in place. So
India benefited from that. But now the
US is changing everything and now India
is under tremendous pressure. The
pressure is going to be for India to
become a US vasal. The next 5 years will
tell us whether this happens or not.
There's a higher likelihood of India
becoming a vasal than not to be very
realistic. Yeah. Um so historical
evidence suggests that such strategies
collapse under systemic crisis like the
one we are facing. The systemic crisis
right that we are seeing right now is a
crisis that the US has manufactured for
its own benefit. What is the crisis? the
systemic crisis, the entire world
so-called rules-based world order, the
system that the Americans had
constructed, they are tearing it down
right now and they are creating a
completely different system. That's a
systemic crisis.
Okay? And the there is an emerging
bipolarity of of sorts. One wonders how
long this bipolarity will last. The
Chinese side and the US side, the
bifurcation of the world global world
order. China, Russia, Iran, Syria, North
Korea, Venezuela. Well, Syria's gone.
Venezuela is gone. So, it's like China,
Russia, Iran, North Korea. Only four
nations left now. Pakistan is no longer
on the Chinese side. Pakistan is a
obedient US lap dog. Now, what if Iran
goes? So, you see the entire system is
being changed. This is a systemic
crisis, complete realignment, re
reordering of the global world order.
And the US knows what it wants from
India in in this new world order they
seek to create. They want India to be an
obedient vasal.
What what what what's going to happen is
the question. It is if you say we have
two choices by
by 2028.
Okay. Wasal
sovereign two choices to be sovereign
we'll have to pay a lot of price prices.
We have to pay a lot. It's going to cost
a lot to remain sovereign. Easy answer,
easy choice, become a vasal.
I think the likelihood of India becoming
a vasal is higher right now by until
2028. If India remains sovereign until
somehow,
then it'll be hard to stop India after
that.
But if you are a smart betting person,
your money will be on India becoming a
vasal.
So that is where we are India. That is
exactly where we are and you can see
what happened in Jabar. India has moved
out of Jabbar. Essentially we have sold
we've liquidated our our stake in
Jabahar
right maybe that's the first step toward
towards perhaps hopefully not but maybe
right let's wait and watch.
Rushab Dare says on one side China
aggressively claims the Shakum valley
Indian army issued statements on the
border situation and said that while our
forces hold our entire territory we are
in a better position which reflects that
our army has not reduced any vigilance
in the border. I don't know what that
entire word salad means but whatever but
the CCP delegation has visited the BJP
and RSS offices and also the office of
other political parties not just the BJP
and the RSS which is not a political
party but the Chinese Communist Party
delegation also visited the headquarters
of other political parties apart from
the BJP
um Indian exports to China are at a
record high is it really a taunt or a
friendmy game talk but only limited
action what's really going on and how
should India stay alert? Okay, answer
the last question first. What should
India do? Stay completely alert visa
with China
completely alert from a military
perspective.
Keep an eye on what the Chinese are
doing north of the India Tibet border,
north of the Pangong Lake, north of the
India Tibet border overall in the
Arunachal sector, in the Ladak sector,
and other sectors. What are the Chinese
doing? They're they're they're bulking
up their military presence. So they'll
talk they'll come to India talk nice
things at the same time they're bulking
up their military presence. So let's not
be fooled. India has to be se vigilance
forever vigilant visa v China. Okay
that's number one. Secondly it's
interesting the Chinese communist party
delegation came to India and uh visited
the headquarters of various political
parties etc. the BJP headquarters, the
RSS which is not a political party but
the parent organization of the BJP, the
CCP delegation visited the the RSS
headquarters and they also visited the
headquarters of several other Indian
political parties. Okay, so it's not
just BJP RSS. Why why this?
Um
maybe it's a routine visit. Maybe the
CCP is trying to send an send a message
to India and the world that we seek
peace and all that. We we seek friendly
relations with India. Maybe that sort of
thing. Or maybe they are genuinely
exploring the possibility of a closer of
maybe some kind some kind of closer
cooperation with a a weaker nation like
India because India is a weaker nation
compared to China. Okay, let's not
forget that. So, so it's like it's like
India
sending a delegation to Nepal or
something. Okay, kind of like that.
Maybe not Nepal, maybe India sending a
delegation to Indonesia.
Okay, Indonesia is about well it's
obviously a major country and a country
that is a very friendly nation of
friendly nation for sure but hard power
wise Indonesia is about 1/4 of India
like India is 1/4 of China right roughly
uh so so it's like India sending a
delegation to Indonesia
so what's going on does this indicate
some kind of dant or a friendmy
I think it's definitely not a donant.
It's too early for it to be don. China
will have to come under more pressure
from the US for it to seriously consider
any kind of friendly they like
relationship with India. Right now it's
just talk talk
China you cannot have a donant with
China unless the Chinese agree to
resolve the India Tibet border issue.
There's no question of a detonant
without that core issue being resolved.
Always remember, always remember this
when it comes to the India China
relationship. The core issue, the
central issue which has been created by
China is China's illegal annexation and
occupation of Tibet and the Chinese
insistence for decades
of not demarcating the India Tibet
border so that India can be kept under
pressure. This entire problem is of
China's making, not our making. So the
onus is on China to solve this. Okay,
that's the deal. So all these visits of
delegations and blah blah blah talk talk
talk talk talk talk talk talk talk talk
talk talk talk talk I don't care about
it
but maybe it indicates potentially
possibly some kind of future
you know improvement potentially in
relations but the only improvement that
makes sense is the demarcation of the
border and there's no step on that
there's there's no move on that at all
so yeah it's all words no actions right
now that that's what it
Rushup says, "What are Zusuli and
Sanguinis respectively? What are the
origins of these terms and their meaning
in American context? Which pattern does
the US follow compared to other major
populations India, China, Russia,
Indonesia, EU, Brazil, African, etc.,
etc., etc., etc. Now, what's the
difference between the two? Juuli and Ju
Sanguinis. And why did the US choose to
give birthright citizenship to its
citizens unlike other countries where
bloodline matters?" Okay. See yusulli
and sanguinis are two systems of giving
citizenship to a person.
Means birth. These are Latin terms.
Okay.
Means birthright citizenship. If you are
born on the territory of a specific
country and they recognize yusulli
then you are automatically a citizen
just by being born on the territory on
the soil of the country. That's husi.
Sanguinius means it doesn't matter where
you're born. If you are a bloodline
descendant of a citizen of of so and so
country, you have the right to be a
citizen of that country.
So the US, so that's bloodline
citizenship. So for India,
if you are born on Indian territory, you
don't automatically get get Indian
citizenship.
You have to prove that either one or
both of your parents is Indian by blood.
So if you are an illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrator who has been living in India
for for 40 years and you have children
and grandchildren then you are not a
citizen of India. Your children are not
citizens of India and your
grandchildrens are also not citizens of
India. They are illegal occupants of
Indian territory. That is what sanguinis
means. So just by being born on on this
soil you don't become a citizen of this
country. That is sanguinis. it rejects
birthright citizenship. Okay. So the US
offers
it it it uh offers birthright
citizenship which means that it
recognizes issues solely. If you're born
there you become a citizen. Why does the
US does? What about India? India doesn't
recognize issues solely. India says only
sanguinis. China also is sanguinist
blood bloodline citizenship not
birthright citizenship. Russia I'm not
sure. You can look up the other
countries what they have. Okay. Brazil
most likely has yoli which means if
you're born in Brazil you are a naturalb
born Brazil Brazilian citizen African
countries maybe it's a mixture of
whatever whatever EU it depends and so
on um so China use sanguines India use
sanguin US soi Brazil soi and US also
recognizes sanguin so let's say your
mother and father are both American
citizens but you were born let's say in
India
So you were not born on US territory.
Then despite you not being born on US
soil, if both your parents or even one
of the parents was an American citizen,
you get American citizenship. So the US
recognizes both
and sanguinis,
right? Um and it depends from country to
country. Now why did the US choose to
give birthright citizenship to its
citizens unlike many other countries?
It's because the US is an artificial
nation.
The US is a nation founded on somebody
else's territory.
It was founded by European occupiers,
colonizers,
on territory taken from other people who
are then um erased out of existence.
So it's a country founded on people
coming from elsewhere and being born and
their children being born here in the in
the US,
right? So let's say you are it's it's
the 1700s
a man comes from England and he meets
another woman who has come from England
and they have a child on North American
soil. So the child obviously will be
recognized as an American citizen.
So because of these special
circumstances in which the US was
created
know stolen land belonging to somebody
else who that those people were
genocided and the people who stole the
land now created a new country out of
it. So because of those special
circumstances of the US being a a nation
of let's say immigrants
that's why the US recognizes you so as
well as you sanguin now okay that's the
deal
Joti Bora says how do you see the
upcoming Artimus 2 mission do you think
ISRO can catch up to NASA when it comes
to crude space missions anytime soon
okay um Arteimus too. So, the US seeks
to send humans back to the moon. The
last human mission to the moon, which
was an American mission, was like 40 50
years ago. When was the last Let's Let's
Google this. Okay. I don't remember.
Like late '7s probably. Last last human
last. Okay. When was the
the last
dude moon landing? Let's see. Okay. It's
early '7s. Gene Cern and Harrison
Schmidt. The last man mission to the
moon was Apollo 17 December 1972
782 92 2002 2012 2012. It's been 54
years
53 years. That's a long time over half a
century that humans haven't set foot on
the moon. So the Americans seek seek to
change this now. So you had the Arteimus
one mission which was launched in 2022
if I am not mistaken and this was um an
uncrrewed mission unmanned mission that
was launched on the SLS system space
launch system system NASA SLS that's the
rocket um and uh it was in 2022 if I'm
not mistaken and it it did this figure 8
orbit of the moon so it goes from the
earth it it loops around the earth and
goes to the moon uh you know shoots
around the moon and then comes back to
earth that sort of thing. Yeah. Uh let's
see. Okay. Arteimus
um Arteimus
one mission. Let's see. So this was when
was it 2022? That's right. I was
absolutely correct. And this is the kind
of uh you know flight path it took.
Okay. It it made it made multiple orbits
of the moon which is fine. Now what will
Artemis 2 do? I think it'll do something
very similar but with human beings this
time only one loop around the moon going
to have four human beings very diverse
crew as as always in America uh one lady
one black person one American male and
one Canadian male very diverse crew so
this is the kind of uh thing it's going
to do so now so it's not a moon landing
mission it's a flyby mission of the moon
so the Arteimus one had dummy crew okay
and It did the thing perfectly
successfully. Now we're going to send
humans who are going to do it's going to
be like a it's going to be like Apollo
8. Apollo 8 did a similar thing before
Apollo 10 actually landed on the moon.
Right. So Optimus 2 is going to do this
loop around the moon and return to the
earth. Before it goes to the moon, it's
going to do a couple of orbits of the
earth and do a docking maneuver or
something to test docking mechanisms and
so on. And then it's going to go to the
moon. Um trans lunar injection and so on
so forth.
Um, and Artemis 2 uses, like I said, the
SLS
uh, rocket, which is the most powerful
rocket that can carry human beings thus
far. Of course, Space X has Starship,
which is probably more powerful than
SLS, but Starship isn't human rated thus
far. SLS is. So uh that is the Arteimus
2 mission and Arteimus 3 perhaps will
send humans on the surface of the moon
if I'm not mistaken. Is that what
Artimus 3 will do will do? We can look
it up. Uh Arteimus 3 is three or three.
Uh Artimus 3 is going to be the first
crude moon landing mission. And do we
know when it happens? Okay, I'm not sure
when it happens.
Um okay, whatever. That's that's in the
future. So, Arteimus 3 is going to be an
actual moon landing. Crude human manned
moon landing. Arteimus 2 is a loop loop
around the moon and come back. So, what
do I think of it? Fantastic. The
Americans have ambition. They don't want
to be left behind in the space race.
They want to take the lead. Let others
catch up. That's the American ethos and
that's admirable, I would say. Can ISRO
catch up? Not anytime soon. India. ISRO.
Look, ISRO doesn't decide what happens,
right? The government of India decides
what this road does and the government
of India has zero ambition right now.
Zero ambition. We have some plans of
humans Indian humans on the moon by 2040
or something whatever. It's all far in
the future. We don't have the rockets
that can take us there that can take
humans there.
Um so ISRO is ISRO is not even in the
race right now. Yeah. No ambition. Not
ISRO government of India. No ambition.
Nothing. So yeah that's the simple
answer.
Okay we discuss history now. Uh Amisha
says after the second world war why were
Korea and Germany parti part partitioned
between occupants between their
occupiers. Okay occupiers while Japan
was solely occupied by just one power
the United States. So after the second
world war ended uh it ended in Germany
with the capture of Berlin and the
disappearance of uh Adolf Hitler.
And then the Asian part of the second
world war ended in August 1945 with the
twin American nuclear tests on the
people of Japan. So that was the end of
the second world war. And when the
second world war ended, you see Germany,
what is the situation in Germany? When
the second world war ended with the fall
of Berlin, the Soviets took Berlin,
the USSR took the majority of Germany
from the east and the allies, the
western allies, they took whatever was
left from the west. So Germany was
already effectively partitioned when the
war ended. The eastern side all USSR
occupied. The western side occupied by
the Americans, the French and the the
Americans, the British and the French.
And that's why Germany had to be
partitioned because the moment the war
ends, the east and the west are
automatically suspicious of each other.
The Americans are automatically
instinctively suspicious of the Soviets.
They have become very powerful. Now we
fear them. Then the Soviets realize the
Americans are treating treating us as
enemies. So let's do it then. Let's have
it. And there was a deal. So that's why
the moment the second world war ended,
Germany was already occupied by two
different forces and that's why it was
partitioned essentially along those
lines. Even Berlin itself was
partitioned. Now uh Korea
when the second world war ended, you had
a situation where the northern part of
Korea um you had Soviet troops there.
Okay? And in the southern part of Korea,
you had American
or Western troops there. So once again,
the moment the war ends, the the the
peninsula is kind of partitioned and
that is what eventually led to the
Korean war and the creation of North and
South Korea and uh that has never
actually ended officially, right? It's
there's never been an actual official
ceasefire. It's a different story. So
that's the deal with Germany as well as
Korea. That's why these two were
partitioned. The actual partition for
Korea happened in the 1950s with the end
of the of the Korean War. Now, what
about Japan? So, when the Americans So,
when Japan um was on the brink of losing
the Second World War, let's let's go to
the map. Okay. Oh, we haven't opened the
map today. Well, that is serious. We
should rectify that immediately. So,
here we are. So, we're going to talk
about Japan. So, let's go back to 1945.
the and at that time see imperial Japan
it had massive territories
uh the large island in the north of
Japan is Saporro it's it's uh Hokkaido
island right Hokkaido Hokkaido and north
of it you have the Kurill Islands the
Kurill Islands belong to Japan I've made
a couple of videos about this in detail
even parts of the Kamchatka Peninsula
uh where they belong to Japan and Sakal
in probably also belong to Japan. Now
Japan is doing poorly in the second
world war. So the Soviets what they do
they take over Kamchatka they take over
Zakalid and they take over the Kurill
Islands as well.
Okay. And then the the atomic bomb tests
happen over Hiroshima and Nakasaki and
Japan surrenders. So so and and then the
Americans take over. But the Americans
can't take over the territories the
Soviets have occupied. So you see this
Kunashir is a Russian territory.
You see how far is it from uh Hokkaido?
If you look at the distance, it's like
24 25 km. So, you can't see it from the
shores, but it's right offshore. What
about this island?
This is a Russian held island. Look at
that. What about this little island
here? That's a Japanese island. Okay.
What about this one here? I think that
that's also Russian territory. So, the
Russians took all these islands. They
took the advantage of Japan's misfortune
and they took all these islands as as
any reasonably rational nation will do.
So even Japan actually its territory was
partitioned right whatever the Americans
were able to occupy they took it and
they still hold it and the rest was held
by the J by the Russians and Japan and
Russia have this territorial dispute
about the the Kural islands and the
Russians aren't giving anything to
Japan.
Okay. So that's what happened. Even
Japan actually was partitioned even
though you may not realize it.
Okay, Nirvana Shanks has a couple of
questions.
Let's take the second one. The one upon
the word the one about Japan.
Many Indians visiting Japan, especially
when standing in temples, notice that
although the language is not understood,
the chants, the mantras, the ritual
recitations sound strangely familiar,
almost reminiscent of mantras heard in
Indian temples. What explains this
perceived similarity in sound and ritual
atmosphere? And what does it reveal
about historical or cultural connections
across Asia? That's the question. So you
see if you watch YouTube videos of
Japanese temple ceremonies and rituals
often you will you'll find that the
Japanese priests are reciting mantras
that you don't really understand but
they sound very much like sankut mantras
and sutras and whatnot and the fire
ceremonies look very much like Indian
yagnas.
Why is that the case? I mean, you'll see
many of these uh YouTube videos all over
the place, you know, uh gooma fire
rituals and whatnot.
One second. Oopsy daisy. So, you have
all these
um one second. Okay, let's find this
video and put it on the screen. For
example, here's an example of a YouTube
video such as that. So, this is Shingon
Buddhist GMA fire ritual, Mount Koa,
Japan. I will not play the video because
there may be copyright issues or
whatever. But you can pause the video,
look up the the title of the video and
if you're interested go and take a look
at the video and you will see many such
uh examples on YouTube. So this is a GMA
fire ritual. They say it is Buddhist but
the ritual is clearly not what you would
consider Buddhist. It's more of a Vic
ritual. It's more of a yagna. And
sometimes you you have Japanese channels
that show this live the recitation of
mantras and sutras and the performance
of these of these uh yagna like rituals
fire uh you know in in involving fire
offering of of various things to the
fire and so on. So why do we have this
incredible similarity? What is the root
of this? Right? You see the truth is the
fact is that India has influenced Japan
for about roughly 2,000 years. Um our
emperor Kesan sent hundreds of of uh
religious missions to the east mainly to
China as part of trade delegations
and this brought Indian culture into
China and the Chinese then transmitted
that into Japan. you know Buddhist
rituals, Vic rituals and so much more.
One of these things is called dan which
the Chinese called which which the
Japanese call Zen, right? Zen Buddhism
they call it. But it's not a Buddhist
thing. It's it's a it's an Indian thing.
So a lot of the Japanese temple rituals,
Shinto rituals, even Buddhist rituals,
they grew out of Sanskrit chanting.
Okay. It traveled from India across
China into Japan. It brought Indian
mantras, Indian sounds, Indian ritual
forms into uh the practices in Japan. So
we have shared roots. Okay. And today
you will find that
the words that are uttered may have
their origin in Sanskrit but they may be
Japanese today. But the rhythm is the
same as what you have chanted in temples
today. Even the phonetics the the the
ucharan the the the the pronunciations
are similar to uh Sanskrit
pronunciation. So many of these mantras
were originally composed in Sanskrit and
they were simply transliterated into
first Chinese and then Japanese
language. Okay, they were not
translated. They were transliterated. So
the phonetic skeleton, the sound
skeleton, the pronunciation,
it still survives in the original forms
in these in these uh in these uh chants
in the temples. And many of these like I
showed you this Shinggon uh GMA fire
ritual. You see there is it's a Shinggon
school of of Japanese Buddhism, Shinto,
whatever probably Buddhism, right? They
still write their mantras in the siddhum
script. What is a siddhum script like?
Let's take a look.
Uh Siddhum script Japan. Let's let's
Google that. Okay. See
Siddhum script.
So it's still used in Japanese temples.
The Siddhum script. Take a look at this.
So you can see it has similarities with
our Danagari script and it is used in
Japanese temples inscriptions etc. Even
today,
this is the Siddhum script. It's also
used in Korea apparently.
As you can see, this is a very
interesting creative use of the Siddhum
script.
So, uh
that's the script that's used in many of
these temples, many of these rituals.
Okay. Um and
the Japanese um katakana the Japanese
alphabet it's a syllary. Okay it's
called katak it's called kana katakana
whatever it is it these also originally
represented the syllables in Sanskrit in
Sanskrit in in in the siddam script or
scripts that encoded or embodied
Sanskrit. So that's why the sound system
once again aligns with Sanskrit style
patterns. So because of these these
matches and these these uh these uh
reasons Japanese priests could and still
can chant Sanskrit sutras and mantras
very fluidly using their script the
katakana script and the sound quality is
very true to the original. So sometimes
it is
Sanskrit, sometimes it is Japanese, but
it sounds very much like the um mantras
that are heard in Indian temple. So
there's a very clear connection between
India and Japan, Indian culture and
Japanese culture, Indian traditions and
rituals and Japanese traditions and
rituals. Essentially Japanese culture is
built, it is founded on a bedrock. The
foundation is of Indian culture. The
bedrock is of Indian culture and on top
of that Japanese traditions have been
built up and to such an extent that
today you can barely see the Indian
elements underneath. But one of the ways
to see that is you know go to these
temples, Shinto temples, Buddhist
temples especially Buddhist temples
where you will treat the temple as a
Buddhist temple. But many of the
traditions and and prayers are not
exactly Buddhist traditions and prayers.
They are what you would call Hindu
traditions and prayers. Many of the gods
and goddesses that are worshiped in
Japan, for example, Ben Zaitin are Hindu
gods and goddesses. Benzin, who is Ben
Zaitin? It's a Japanese goddess, a kami.
But what is the original form of benzin?
It is Saraswati.
Benin. There we have it. Benjitin is the
Japanese version of Saraswati very
clearly.
Okay. Then you have Kangitin. Who is
Kangitin?
Kangitan is Vinayaka.
All right. Kangitan is is Lord Ganesh.
And u Yeah. So you have all the Indian
gods and goddesses that are present in
Japan. And these are not Buddhist gods
and goddesses. These are Hindu gods and
goddesses that are regarded as regarded
as Japanese gods and goddesses or maybe
Buddhist gods and goddesses. Kami.
So there are there's this deep
connection that India has with Japan.
The people of Japan may not be
completely aware of that today. And when
Indians visit Japan, you will find these
striking parallels. And you'll be like,
what? What am I hearing? What am I
seeing here? Why is it so why why does
it sound so similar, so familiar? This
is the reason why.
Okay. Okay. Swapnel Mishra says if
Africa
if Africa had uh been organized into
five large regional states, north, east,
west, central and southern Africa rather
than fragmented into many smaller
nations, how might their economic
development and global competitiveness
have differed? The question is
interesting. If Africa had been divided
up in carved up into these zones into
all these small nations, would they have
would these African regions have done
better? Would they have been uh governed
better? Would they have been
economically better off, more
prosperous? Would the living standards
be better? Would they be globally more
competitive than the current shape and
form of African nations today? What
would have been the outcome of this sort
of thing? Well, we can do the thought
experiment today. Where is the map? Here
is map. Yes, we bring map.
So today if you look at the map of
Africa,
you'll see that it has all these
nations. Many of the nations are
artificially created nations with
straight lines clearly drawn by
Europeans on a map, right? Uh most of
these nations have straight line borders
or borders that have significant
straight line elements. I mean I can't
think of a single African nation that
doesn't have significant straight line
elements. Right? So all of these borders
were drawn by Europeans. Leoto is is
more organic. Madagascar doesn't count
because it is an island. But here we
have it. So let's say we draw straight
lines such that we have a northern part
of Africa, southern part of Africa,
east, west, and central.
Would that have provided better outcomes
for Africa? You see,
there's multiple factors that go into
whether there's going to be a better
outcome in this case or not. First is
what sort of ethnic composition do you
have in one of these zones. See in the
real world there is competition there's
adversariality and so much more. So
let's say you have multiple ethnic
groups who have been living in various
parts of Africa for a long time. They
will have their own histories. Some of
the ethnic groups will not be
compatible. Maybe they have centuries
long enmities. You put them together in
one country you're going to have civil
war.
That may not happen if you have a strong
government and strong military. But who
will guarantee that? Let's say for
example,
let's say you you do this experiment not
in Africa but in um in West Asia. Let's
say you create a West Asia country
which in includes Turkey,
it Iraq. Let's say it includes Turkey,
Syria, Jordan, Israel and Greece. Now
Greece and Turkey, you put them
together, that's a volatile combination.
You have a nation that includes Greece
and Turkey, that is a recipe for
disaster, my dear friends. Okay? That's
a recipe for disaster. The Greeks and
Turks hate each other. You include
Armenia in that, it's going to be
another recipe for disaster because the
Turks want to kill off the Armenians.
So, it doesn't work. It simply can't
work. That nation is doomed before it it
starts. What if you create a nation that
includes Iran, Iraq, and Saudi Arabia?
Do you think it that will work? It can't
work. The Saudis and Iraqis are you can
say that Iraqis are Arabs and Saudis are
obviously Arabs, but Iranians are not
Arabs. They're Aryans. You can't put
them in a nation that is half Arab. It
doesn't work culturally, ethnically.
Doesn't work. And it's the Shiauri thing
also. It simply it won't work. So you
see these artificial conceptions of
artificial nations,
it it can be a bigger disaster than than
a solution to to a problem. So if you
look at Africa, we don't know much about
Africa because we haven't taught about
it. But if you transpose that solution
to other parts of the world, it
immediately becomes glaringly clear it's
not going to work. Right? So this
thought experiment if it had been
conducted in Africa, it probably would
not have given the desired results.
First of all, because of the fact that
so many of these tribes and ethnic
groups and all they have their ancient
rivalries and and issues and problems
and also then the question becomes who
rules this this artificial country? If
the a guy from this ethnic group rules
it, other people will feel agrieved. If
a guy from that ethnic group rules it,
then these people will feel agrieved and
you can't satisfy them all. So ideally
you should have countries based on a
single culture, civilization or ethnic
group, right? sometimes religion I
suppose but religion doesn't always uh
solve those problems
so it may not have worked out that's the
point I'm making all right
okay
okay Malik says I live in Deken part of
India my family is a Syad family which
has a lineage going back to the prophet
of Islam and we are believed to be the
descendants of the prophet I've heard
from my m maternal side that my
ancestors from the maternal side were
Shia sayy the people from Yemen
who migrated to the Dean in India, Deken
region of India about 4 centuries ago,
400 years ago. And from my paternal
side, I have heard that my paternal
ancestry dates back to the migration of
Saiyad family from Baghdad, the Mashad
Isan, that area of Persia about a
thousand years ago to India because of
oppression and killing of Syads. Hindu
kings wrote letters and invited us to
India and gave us shelter after hearing
the oppression uh to us caused by
nobility of lineage. How true are these
migration patterns? We have records that
show migration of sayyad, Imam to imams
to various parts of India such as
Lacnau, Hyderabad, Bidar, Kashmir etc.
always grateful and thankful for India
for letting us live here and settle
here. All right. So
we know that there are these old records
or at least stories passed down in in
families over generations
u of migrations
from let's say from Yemen from Baghdad
from Mashad from Isvahan. So Yemen is
obviously south of the Arabian
Peninsula. Baghdad is the capital
historical historic capital of
Mesopotamia Iraq right then and you have
Mashad is Fahan etc. These are major
cities in Turkey. Sorry, in in Persia,
in Iran, right? So Yemen is Arabic.
Baghdad is Mesopotamia which is now
Arabic. Then you have Mashad and Isahan
which is Persian which is Arian. So
um so these are the places from which
clearly people did indeed over the past
several centuries migrate to India and
settle in India. And obviously if that's
happened, you're going to have stories
passed on over the generations and
families, right? But can we v verify
these these migration patterns, these
these narratives? We know that there
there has been historically proven well
attested migration from West Asia,
various parts of West Asia to India.
Small numbers of people migrating and
settling in various parts of India.
Right? But
how precise are specific claims you know
that from my mother's side let's say 400
years ago uh there was migration from so
and so place how precisely can you
corroborate that or maybe from my
father's side 1,000 years ago some you
know they came from whatever is vahan or
whatever can you actually precisely
verify that you know this unbroken and
and the claim of the unbroken descent
from the prophet of Islam
Can you confirm that in detail? You
cannot specifically corroborate the
precise claims but the broad migration
patterns are reasonably well known and
very well established. So if we look at
um
for example look um we have I mean
various genetic research papers do exist
with that kind of speak about this in in
broad terms. There is this research
paper called origins of the Indian sad
tribe a genetic perspective by Zahedan
uh who is okay this is a Pakistani
person government college university
lahor origins of the Indian side tribe
genetic perspective and you can read the
whole thing so it does kind of confirm
that you know uh
people in various parts of India
including the region uh they do have
some ancestry from west Asia Now
everybody who claims West Asian ancestry
will not have it. Actually it's a
minority of people who claim West Asian
ancestry will have it. Um so in the Dean
region we have uh historically known
that Persian and Arabic origin people
settled in places like like Bijapur,
Golanda, Hyderabad etc. Right. Um and
obviously if they settle from those
regions, you're going to have some
today's people who today the descendants
today will have a little bit of West
Asian ancestry. But it definitely
indicates there is direct lineage that
comes from West Asia for those people.
Even if only 3% of your oral ancestry
today or DNA today is of West Asian
origin, the rest will be obviously of
subcontinental origin. But you still
have a direct lineage. But uh and so
that is about uh the Deacon region. Then
also you have clusters of say uh
communities in uh in Lacno region and
whatnot that came from maybe Iran or
Iraq that sort of place in West Asia
and uh in the Islamic societies there
there were these genealogical practices
for say families where families you know
kept detailed records of their ancestry
right and the thing is that having say
ancestry or belonging to say the family
which means you are a descendant of the
prophet it is a prestigious thing in
Islamic communities right so
sometimes these trees you know these
genetic trees or these these trees of
lineage that were written they became
tools of status if you could show a
genetic lineage or or or you know a
lineage that traced all the way back to
prophet Muhammad then it it was very
prestigious so sometimes it's been known
that some people would kind of sometimes
edit that and make
make it work like that to become an
elite person in in Islamic society and
so on.
Um so it's known that um
we have some communities in India
uh whether it's in the in the Dean or in
North India where you have higher
incidence of West Asian ancestry.
See most Indian Muslims have zero West
Asian ancestry. Most Indian Muslims are
100% u subcontinental
in terms of their DNA but there are
specific clusters of of people in
various parts of India who do have known
West Asian ancestry right so that is
known but you can't know for sure
whether you are descended from from the
prophet and uh
and you can't trace it back entirely
that's the point so if If your family
has passed down the knowledge of its
descent over many generations from both
sides then I think uh you should instead
of trying to verify it which will which
is not going to happen you should I
think cherish it right that you know
more about your ancestry than most
people do I mean how many people in the
world today know what their great great
grandfather's name was what he or she
did what he did right how many
Two generations ago, you had four
grandparents.
Three generations ago, you had what?
Eight grandparents. 10 generations ago,
you can do the math. So, you have so
many sources of ancestry. And knowing
even one of those like 400 years ago,
thousand years ago, it's a big deal. So,
um you can't really trace it back. You
can't really corroborate it. You can't
really verify it. But it is known that
you have clusters of population
population groups in India who have
elevated West Asian ancestry uh compared
to the rest of Indians who don't have
it. So
that's what I can say. I don't have a
specific answer to you but it is known
through genetic studies. There are
people in India who have Westian
ancestry. So in so maybe you are that in
that case some of your ancestors did
come from those parts of the world which
is fantastic you know. Yeah. So we all
we also glad to have you. What can I
say? Glad to have you. All right.
Bringan says, "Why did Pam change his
name to Garib Navas? Isn't it a
coincidence when Orurange almost
conquered the whole of India, much of
the subcontinent in 1705, Pamiba was
ruling Manipur from 1709 to 1748. Assam
was occupied by the Muggals for a short
period of time. But Manipur was the only
major Hindu kingdom with a large land
area which the muggles could not occupy.
Right. What was Pamiba's original name?
Was it Chintang Kumba? What was it? Let
me see.
I don't recall exactly what was his
actual real name.
Yeah, he called himself Gibb Nawaz.
His dad was pitarayonga
and his actual name
yeah his name was Pameiba and he was
also called Gopal Singh and at some
point in time he decided that he will be
called Gibbaz's
name was King Pambar Chayanga.
So why did Pameiba okay first of all I
just took a look at Wikipedia for
convenience always remember Wikipedia is
not necessarily a reliable source of
information. Now why did Pamea change
his name to Garib Noas? I think it was
the the the Turk and Persian influence.
The whole of essentially the whole of
the subcontinent was occupied by the
Turks under Orurange Ze right. So there
was a lot of Turk and Persian influence
all across India. And I suppose
did not really realize that this is not
exactly u a term that is Indian in
origin perhaps
right and it is the term it's a term
that
it's not Indian I suppose he just maybe
that influence came in through Bengal
because Manipur was strongly influenced
by from Bengal right um
Shanti Das Kosai and uh
who else I forget the names all the the
the Gordia
you know the people who propagated
Gordioism into Manipur I think Shantas
Kosai was one of those people so they
came from Bengal Bengal was under strong
Turic influence at the time maybe
occupation as well right so these things
they percolate into into common usage
and gur noas means the he who helps the
gur people and all that something like
that. So I suppose he thought that you
know this is a nice name to have. Let me
call myself Karib Naz. It is definitely
not a Manipuri name. It's not not an
Indian term not a Manipuri it's not a
term that originates in the Manipuri
language the Miy language. It's
obviously not a term that originates in
any Indian languages. It's obviously
either probably Persian or Turk. No not
not Turk either Persian or Arabic. So
that's the influence that foreign
occupation has on a society culture
civilization. Right.
Amisha says, "Why is Indo-European
called Indo-Germanic in German since it
doesn't just include Indian and Germanic
languages?
I think that it's it's obviously
a leftover of the 19th century. In the
19th century, it was the Germans who,
you know, created, let's say, the field
of indology. The Germans were very
interested in India. The Germans, the
Germans, they sought to steal Indian
heritage. Why? And how?
You see, Germany doesn't have its own
history.
Germany was never unified ever before
1871 as a single kingdom, a single
empire or a single civilization, single
culture ever. It was always a small
fragmented bunch of kingdoms and
principalities and duchies and whatnot.
It's only in 1875 that the 1871 that it
was unified as a single entity by the
iron chanc.
So the Germans sought some kind of
legitimacy for their culture civil
whatever you know not civilization they
don't have a civilization but you know
that they sought something that gave
them an air of antiquity.
So one thing they proposed or or claimed
is that all the Nordic languages are
Germanic languages Tutonic Germanic
whatever. So the Danish language the
Norwegian language the Swedish Swedish
Swedish Swedish language etc. These are
all Germanic language. English is
Germanic, right? They they so the idea
was they they put forth at the time and
it was very successfully received
everywhere is that all these northern
European languages are Germanic
languages
and these are the languages that are at
the extreme western end of Europe.
And it was very clear that the oldest of
all these languages that are all
interrelated was Sanskrit in the far
east. I mean from from where they were
sitting it's far far in the east India
right so the idea was that there is one
single language family all the way east
in India east in India you have the
Indian languages of which Sanskrit is
the oldest and all the way west in the
European realm we have the Germanic
language the other extreme the western
extreme so India in the east the
Germanic language in the west that's why
they called this language family
Indo-Germanic obviously also it also
included the romance languages the
italic languages Slavic languages, the
Persian language and so much more.
But the two extremes they said one is
Indian, one is Germanic. So that's
called it Indo-Germanic.
And I think even today they call it
Indo-Germanic in German. In the other
languages, English etc. It's called
Indo-Uropean. But the Germans I think
they still call it Indo-Germanic. Let's
let's see. Indo-Germanish.
Let's see. Indoish.
Is it like that? Indo-Germanic.
Germanish sprain.
Indo-Germanish German for Indo-Germanic
is a traditional German term for the
Indo. Yeah. The traditional German term
for the Indo-Uropean language family
blah blah blah blah blah etc etc etc
synonym linguist Indo-Germananish is the
German scientific term for the
Indo-uropean language family etc. So
they still use this term Indo-Germanish
then you have the and blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah. So okay some other
people are also asking this question
whatever. Okay.
So that's the deal. That's about
Indo-Germanic. And the Germans, they
sought to steal Indian cultural
civilizational ideas and assign them to
German. So that's why the Arian invasion
theory was invented. You know that it
was very well known that Sanskrit is the
oldest of the Indo-Uropean languages by
by far.
But then the Max Mill Müller proposed
the idea that you know what the Indians
are brown people but their ancestors
were white because the original Indians
were black and their white ancestors
came from the Germanic speaking world
the Arian world. So that's why the Arian
race is the greatest race and the real
Arians are the white people. They stole
the term area from India and Persia
and they stole the whole language family
because Germany did not have any real
history of its own. So it sought to
steal Indian history. I'm not saying all
Germans do this. It's the German
intellectuals, so-called intellectuals.
Even today their geneticists try to
harp on about the Arian invasion theory
and somehow seek to support it. Arian
invasion, migration, tourism, picnic,
alien alien invasion theory, whatever
you want to call it.
Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "The Ming dynasty
isolated itself from the world despite
having a strong naval capacity.
How did this choice affect China's
future global rule?" Well, what an
important question. What a precient
question. The Ming dynasty, it's 1300s,
1400s, is it? Let's let's and and Janggh
the Chinese admiral, am I right? 1300s,
1400s. Let's see. Okay. Ming dynasty.
Ming dynasty.
1300s 14. Yeah, see I was right. 1300s.
So 1368 to 1644. Now what about Janggh?
That guy was late 1300s, early 1400s if
I'm not mistaken. I'm usually bad with
dates. Let me see if I turn out to be
right.
Janghi.
Uh yes, late 1300s, early 1400s. I was
right. Once again, see I'm I'm right
when it comes to dates approximately. I
don't bother to memorize dates, but I'm
approximately correct with dates. So you
have the Ming dynasty
1300s to 1600s and they had a good naval
capacity. They could build pretty large
ships, pretty massive ships and put
weapons that were reasonably scary on
those ships, reasonably advanced
technology for its time. And they could
send entire flotillas of those ships
together, task forces together. And they
had a great admiral the Hi general
Janggh who was also a unique a unic. A
unic is a person who has to undergo a
certain who has undergone a certain
surgical procedure the Chinese practice
charing. So he was this unuk admiral
u and he was uh sent by the Chinese Ming
dynasty on several expeditions uh to
discover the world and to project
Chinese power and one of the places
where they did this was Sri Lanka and
they also I suppose went to East Africa
and so on those allegedly if I'm not
mistaken you can look it up so so during
the Ming dynasty the Chinese had
significant naval capabilities and they
had the ability to travel far and wide
and project power as well, military
power, right? And then later Ming kings,
emperors, whatever you want to call
them, they decided to no longer exercise
or use the Chinese naval capacity. Shut
it down. Not interested. They decided to
focus on the land borders. They decided
to focus on um keeping an eye on
Mongolia because Mongolia was is
powerful. Yes, very powerful. They had
already been burned by the Mongols
before Shir Chingish Khan, Shirik Kabla
Khan and so on. So they said okay we
will now focus on the land borders. We
will we will um defend the land borders.
We will turn inwards. We'll become
insular. We'll forget about the sea sea
stuff, ocean stuff. Why do we need to do
all this? What's the big deal? Forget
about it. And so they voluntarily
essentially dismantled their naval
capabilities. So the we talking about
this. So the Ming dynasty lasts until
the 1600s, right? So that's by the 1600s
it's clear that they have dismantled
essentially voluntarily the Chinese
naval capabilities. What's the outcome
of this long-term outcome? So 16 let's
say 1640 they have dismantled the
Chinese naval capabilities.
Go forward a couple of hundred years
1840s what does China face?
Naval invasions from the Europeans.
The Europeans did not dismantle naval
capabilities. They built on top of their
existing naval capabilities. Europe was
far away from China. China didn't did
not even know that Europe existed
mostly.
But 200 years after this, after the Ming
dynasty, the Chinese find that the
Europeans have super advanced naval
capabilities. They have militarized
those naval capabilities. They have
created a world order that is euroentric
in nature. They dominate the seas. They
decide what happens in the on the seas.
They decide who controls the trade
routes and who can use the trade routes.
And they are now imposing terms on
China.
That is the beginning of the Chinese
century of humiliation. So because the
Ning dynasty voluntarily
dismantled its naval capabilities, China
had to pay a huge huge price 200 years
later. Huge price. A century of
humiliation.
How stupid does it look in hindsight? It
may have made sense when the Ming
Emperor decided we don't need to do this
anymore. But 200 years later, it looked
so stupid and it was a terrible
decision. If the Chinese had expanded on
their naval capabilities, they would
have pushed the Europeans out of the
ocean.
But the that's not what happened. So the
these small choices make such a huge
difference. Today India is treating ISRO
with a strep motherly treatment. We have
the the space capabilities. We are
choosing to disregard them.
Five space launches, five rocket
launches a year, six rocket launches a
year. PSLV is failing. Who cares? Space
ah Janedo
who cares.
So
that took 200 years. This will take 20
years in the 21st century. In the 21st
centuries, all the time scales are
compressed.
In 20 years, you will need a visa to go
to space. The Americans will say, "Sra
wants to do a space launch. Apply for
permission. Wait in line for 6 months."
What will you do then?
Unless we build a permanent presence in
in space, in which case they can't do a
thing. But no, we are just snoozing
right now. We are going backwards.
So, this is a cautionary tale. the Ming
dynasty's
decision to isolate itself and and cut
down its naval capability. That's that's
exactly what we are doing with Israel.
We not taking it forward. It's just
floating wherever it is. Zero ambition
from the government of India right now.
It's it's distressing to see. Next
question.
Amisha says, why did the imperial
Japanese keep the French colonial regime
in power during their occupation of
Indochina? We're talking about 1940,
1941, right? The Japanese Empire has
marched across Asia eastwards, sorry,
westwards, and they have now conquered
Indochina. And yet they allowed the
French colonial regime to stay in power.
What is Indochina? What is Indochina?
It's Cambodia, Vietnam, Laos. That's
Indochina. Where's the map? We go to the
map and we'll talk about that. All
right. All right. Okay. Where is it? Um,
where is map? We put map on the screen.
We talk about the Indochina.
So Indo-China
is today's Vietnam, Cambodia and Laos.
That is Indochina and it was ruled by
the French. So in 1940 1941 the Japanese
roll in and they take control of the
place and they allow the French
government to remain in power.
Why is that is the question. See at the
time the Japanese
their objective was to prevent the
allies the see the allies means the
British and the Americans right mainly
now the allies where did they exist in
Asia in India the British occupied India
at the time they had been occupying
India for two and a half centuries very
brutally
and as a consequence the Americans were
able to use various air bas sorry excuse
me air bases in various parts of India
to supply
Chinese forces against Russ against
Japan. So the Japanese intended to cut
off these supplies the the allied
ability to supply resupply China and
so they wanted to as a consequence use
Indochina as a staging base for a
further invasion westwards eventually
into Burma eventually into India and
possibly into China as well. Okay. Now
the thing is this in 1940 the French
government that that that ruled
Indo-China it was the Vishi government
the Vishi government was under Nazi
control. See, in the beginning of the of
the Second World War, very quickly, the
Germans were able to conquer and occupy
France and they set up a puppet regime
in France in Paris, the Vishi regime,
which was a a collaborator regime of the
uh that actually u served the Nazis that
served Nazi Germany. So the French
government at the time served Nazi
Germany and this was the French
government that was ruling Indochina and
the Japanese were aligned or allied with
the Nazis.
So instead of removing this government
that was technically allied with them,
they said you know what we will simply
use Indochina for a as a place as a base
from which we will launch further
invasions for the westwards and
northwards and we don't want to take the
trouble of setting up a new government
and doing all that in Indochina. Let the
French do that job. We don't want to
bring in thousands of more Japanese to
administer the place. We just want to
use the place as a base from which to
launch further invasions. So it made
sense to allow the French to do whatever
they're doing and uh and simply use
Indochina as as a place from which to as
a springboard from which to launch
further invasions.
Of course eventually the Japanese did a
regime change even there in Indochina.
Yeah. What 44 45 around that time that's
when the tide had turned. Right.
Right. Okay.
Uh, Diva Aspasputra says, "I was driving
alone in snow in deep snow with in heavy
snowfall when I heard you made that
comment on quantum dance. It cracked me
cracked me up so bad I almost skip. I
hope you're okay. I hope you don't
completely skip." Uh, tell us a bit
about how the US made the Philippines
its colony. How did a postcolonial state
end up owning its own own colony?
Postcolonial state, the US ended up
owning a colony of its own. The
Philippines, where is the Philippines?
Let's go to the map maps quickly and
find out where the Philippines are. The
Philippines are over here north of
Indonesia. These nation this these this
archipelago. Okay, that is the
Philippines. South of Taiwan uh east of
Vietnam across the Champa Sea or the
so-called South China Sea and north of
Indonesia and that's the Philippines. So
the Philippines were occupied by the
United States. Okay, how did that
happen? Well, you see, for the longest
time, the Philippines were occupied by
Spain.
By Spain, Spain. Then the Filipino
people said, "We are tired of Spanish
occupation and colonization of
Philippines, the evil, nasty people." So
the Filipinos rose up in revolt against
Spain. And they fought the Spaniards
militarily and they set up a parallel
rebel government in the Philippines,
1898 or somewhere.
At the time the US also fought the
Spaniards
and they defeated the Spaniards and then
they signed a treaty in Paris the
Americans with the Spaniards. In this
treaty they gave this the Americans the
US gave Spain $20 million or whatever it
was to purchase Philippines
and completely disregarded the the fact
that the Philippines Filipino people had
set up their own government. So the
Filipino people had set up their own
government in in the Philippines. But
the Americans simply bought the
Philippines from from Spain after
defeating Spain in a war. The Americans
do this. They buy the Louis Louisiana
purchase, the Alaska purchase, the
Philippines purchase. Now they're
talking about the Greenland purchase.
They simply do that. So they bought the
nation and the people. They bought the
people to the Americans. This is the
history of the America. Americans. Okay.
So 7 so 1898 they buy the Philippines
from Spain and then the Filipinos say no
we will not be treated as a possession.
So so they fight the Americans and that
fight goes on for a while and the
Americans do all kinds of nasty brutal
things to the Filipinos. Okay.
And that's how the Americans made the
Philippines its own their own colony and
they imposed English on the Filipinos
and they imposed further Christianity on
the Filipinos and the American style of
education and so on. And this entire
situation went on until the Japanese
occupied the Philippines in the second
world war. Eventually Japan lost and
1945 or thereabouts the Philippines were
freed again from the Japanese come again
under American occupation and then the
Americans say okay let's move out of
this place in 1946. So 1946 is when the
Philippines actually become independent
but they still have American naval bases
and so on Bay and whatnot. So that's the
long the short form of the story of how
the Philippines became a colony of the
Americans.
Okay. Amisha says, "How did no not how
did did pockets of paganism survive in
medieval Europe after Christianization?"
Yes, they did. See,
Christianity was imposed on the
Europeans by force. But even though it
was imposed by force, it was difficult
to control the Europeans. So what the
Christians would do, the Christian
converters and colonizers and the and
the church officials and all they would
what they would do is the Europeans had
their ancient religion which was nothing
but a continuation of the Indian Vic
religion. The same religion in different
shapes and forms, same gods and
goddesses in different shapes and forms.
So the Europeans had this practice of
having temples. They had this practice
of having sacred mounds and hills. They
had the practice of having uh sacred
wells and sacred groves of trees. So the
so the Christians would do what? They
would destroy the the the
pre-Christian temples and build a church
there so that the worship would be
continuous in the same place and it
would be easier to convince the
Europeans, you know, to keep worshiping
in the same sacred place. But now it's a
church and it's now it's Jes Jesus
Christ. It's no longer your gods and
goddesses. Similarly
the practice you know there was
something called called bad Christianity
or something in which various uh
pre-Christian traditions were continued
within Christianity.
You know certain places were regarded as
sacred. Everyone knew that these are
pre-Christian sacred places and all and
that also continued. Um and some parts
of Europe simply did not become
Christian for a very long time. Certain
Slavic regions became Christian only in
the 19th century or 18th or 19th
centuries. You know Lithuania barely
became Christian Lithuania and all they
continued many pagan traditions as
syncric traditions within Christianity.
Uh there are many cathedrals that have
clearly non-Christian symbols in them.
Um in Russia in the Slavic regions like
I said there were many places where
Christianity barely existed. It was
barely practiced. Uh there was this very
famous Russian Orthodox Christian monk
called Rasputin.
He was regarded as a pagan so strong
where where it pagan pagan practices. U
so yeah it was like that in different
parts of Europe. the the church tried to
hammer everybody into submission and
they tried to impose Christianity
everywhere but it succeeded in at
different levels in different places. In
some places you had clear synratism um
of and and and various sacred festivals
pre-Christian festivals were then
absorbed into Christianity and Christian
symbolism was superimposed on top of
those. Uh, the winter solstice is what?
December 22 or something. But it was
turned into December 25, Christmas, that
sort of thing. 22 23 is the solstice,
right? Which is the winter solstice? One
second. Give me a second. I'm sure it's
December 22/23.
Uh, winter solstice
21 December. Okay. So, a few days ago.
So, that was turned into into Christmas
December 25. Maybe it was 25 earlier,
maybe 2,000 years ago, whatever it was.
So that that's what was done. And a lot
of these pre-Christian practices somehow
managed to survive despite the
Christianization and so on. So you had
pockets of paganism did which did
survive uh in Europe after
Christianization or despite the
Christianization and uh in the 20th
century you have had the revival of of
of pre-Christian uh religions and so on.
In uh in the Nordic countries, you have
something called Asatru, which is a
revival revivalist form of the Nordic
paganism with the old gods, you know,
Thor, Odin, Voden, so on so forth,
Freya, Idrasil, and so on. And
in the in the Baltic no in the in the
Lithuania Latvia region you have the
revival of Ruba which is the old
religion and it sometimes they have to
bring in priests from outside. Okay.
Romeova.
So it's the it's a neopagan religion you
know based on the old uh old culture and
religion of Lithuania. And sometimes
they have to bring in priests from
outside of Europe. Priests who know the
old traditions better. For example,
one second. Let's open that. Give me a
second. So sometimes for practicing the
room religion, they have to bring in
priests from outside who know the old
traditions and religion better. So here
you have a Hindu priest officiating at a
room ritual because it is the same
religion. Either way, FYI, right?
So, yeah, it's it's kind of still
survives and some people are trying to
revive the old culture, which well, good
for them. I wish them the best.
And that should I still have multiple
more questions,
but
I've gone significantly below the
beyond the 2our mark. So, let me end
this here and let me see if Okay.
And now I can see that I've got 19 super
chats that I need to take up. So let's
quickly go through the super chats and
then we shall call it a day.
Minimalist Maverick says with Iran
regime change, will I become will
IG become next UA for Russia?
With Iran regime change, will Iran
become the next Ukraine for Russia? No,
it won't. Very unlikely. Uh Namaste
Praam. Namaste Praam. Thank you very
much. Thank you. Uh Mac
M 4 says after new UGC rules do you
think BJP is equally compromised as
Congress no action by them on illegal
immigrants feeling depressed about Hindu
future. Look as you all know very well I
don't need to remind you all I do not
comment about internal matters of India
but I what I can say is that the UGC
rules new rules whatever I'm seeing are
terrible terrible they seek to create a
permanent divide in India oppressor and
oppressed
okay so certain categories of people are
forever oppressed and certain certain
categories of people are forever
oppressors
So certain so those who are being
labeled as oppressors
you can make any allegation against
about them and they have to pay the
price. People will just simply leave the
country off if if this is you know
brought into effect. So I think it's
it's terrible. I don't know what the
government of India is doing. That's all
I I'll say about this.
Namaste core difference between
between
Visual and Iran. One fell, the other
didn't. Iran is way more powerful than
than Venezuela. Iran can hit back.
Iran can hit back very strongly. It has
very large stockpiles of very very very
capable missiles. Iran sits on massive
oil reserves. Iran can destroy the oil
wells of all the surrounding countries
if it wants. Iran has a lot of leverage,
you know, that Venezuela doesn't. So
that's the core difference. Uh Brute
Cole says, "I am a I am a undergraduate
student in in chemistry at IIT. I want
to pursue MS in quantum information
technologies abroad. Please tell me
whether I should go to China, west of
Japan. Also tell about this future
scope. Okay, listen. Um I don't know
about the landscape the the educational
landscape when it comes to quantum
information technology. I think the US
will be the best country for that. I'm
sure the Chinese also of course are
trying to catch up catch up with the US
in in
every technology you can imagine quantum
information technologies very very very
cutting edge uh field so I'm sure China
has great opportunities uh educational
opportunities when it comes to quantum
information technologies obviously I'm
I'm I'm guessing I have not seen I don't
look into these things I don't look into
which which country offers the best
education opportunities and so and so I
don't look into that I'm not in that
field but I am pretty sure it must be
there in China. So you need to do your
own research. You need to do your own
due diligence. Okay. The US probably
will be the best place to study this.
China may be the next best possibly.
Japan I'm not sure. Japan is not allowed
to do research in certain technology. So
I'm not sure. So west definitely the US
number one place. Number two will be
China. I don't know about Australia. I
don't think Australia may be the right
place for this. When it comes to Europe,
I would say I'm not sure, Germany,
whatever. I think I would I would say
it's either either the US or China.
Definitely nothing in India. I'm sure.
Okay. So, all the best. Do well. Uh make
the right choice. Do your research
properly and uh do well. I wish you
success. All the best.
Gati says, "Is it true that India has
left?" Yes, India has left. India has
liquidated its stake in Chabahar. has
given whatever the money
it was worth to Iran.
Uh so for all the bravado that Janker
gives about strategic autonomy also have
you observed this historical pattern
where
when Iran falls India falls next we
should help Iran there's nothing we can
do to help. So first of all India has
liquidated its stake in Chabahar port
when it when we were faced with US
pressure we had to do that. So we have
caved in
wise thing to do.
Okay. There's nothing we could have done
to stop this. We would have paid a
price. Way more tariffs on India. And
anyway, if the Americans do a regime
change or destroy the Chabaha airport,
what do we do? Best to exit it. It is
the wise thing to do. India is a weak
nation right now. Relatively relatively
much weaker than the US. This is the
best thing we can do. See the past 10-15
years, India has been doing the exact
opposite of hide your strength and bide
your time. India has been the exact
opposite of that extremely unwisely.
India has this this this tendency of
boasting boasting boasting instead of
keeping quiet. So now it's going to all
going to fall flat. But we are still a
sovereign nation.
But the beginning of wasalloud starts.
How does it start? When your foreign
policy actions start being dictated by
outsiders and that's what's happened
here for India. Until now, our leaders
have been saying right no third party
can tell us what we will do. We decide
what to do. No longer the case. This is
a very dangerous sign.
This is how Vasalude begins. I'm not
saying India is becoming a vasal right
now. But this is how it begins. Uh the
historical pattern where when Iran
falls, India falls next.
Well, it's happened once
the Arabic invasions, right? Yeah. Iran
fell, then India fell.
We should help Iran. We can help Iran if
we are a powerful nation. We can't even
help the Hindus of Bangladesh. We can't
even help the Hindus of Pakistan.
We can't even prevent the Chinese from
interfering in Nepal. And we want to
help Iran. Not going to happen. We're
not strong enough. Facts.
Facts.
Arian Shukla says, "What are the losses
due to internet shutdown like in Iran?
Can they keep it down for a longer
time?" What are the losses? What kind of
losses?
What are the losses due to internet
shutdown like in Iran? Can they keep it
down for a longer time? The Iranian
government keep can keep internet
shutdown as long as it wants, right? It
controls the internet in its country.
It's a sovereign nation. The government
decides what happens. They can keep it
down for the next 3 months if they want.
What are the losses? I don't I have no
idea what are the losses. What kind of
losses do Iranian uh businesses depend
on the internet? I'm not sure about
that. So So the government of Iran can
keep it down as long as they want. 3
months, 6 months, 3 years, whatever.
It's their choice. Losses, I have no
idea, sir. I have no idea.
Abra Shkar says, "Could you or someone
you know at some point start a channel
for rare earthy or cicers?" I can't. I'm
not an expert in this domain. Somebody I
know I don't know any experts in this
domain. I may know some people who are
in IITs or whatever, but they are doing
IIT work. They won't start channels
doing this. So, and it's a very niche
topic.
Rare earth methology. Anyway, I I'll see
if I can talk to somebody if maybe you
can start it. I'm not the person to do
it cuz I'm not an expert in this. I can
be an expert in this if I spend the next
3 to 6 months studying it because I have
the
the background to understand this. Maybe
not even 3 months
probably a couple of months of intensive
study I could definitely have expert
level knowledge in this because I have
the physics background but it's not for
me. Anyway, thank you for the
suggestion. I'll see if if something can
be done.
Jagjit Mida says what drives wars
national interest or arms lobby? Both
can drive wars. Sometimes in some
nations the arms lobby can also precede
the national interest.
Right?
In an ideal world everything is driven
by the national interest or everything
should be driven by the national
interest. But in some nations,
in some nations you may have a situation
where vested interests supersede the
national interest
and or they they they construe their
interest as a national interest. In that
case, if it's an arms lobby, they can
start wars. So it can happen, right?
It's not an ideal world we live in. So
arms lobbies can indeed spark wars or
drive wars at times. Yeah.
says, "Is Bahrain on red alert now in
case of US war with Iran?" I think all
the nations in the West Asia region are
on high alert. What nations are these?
Let's quickly take a look at the map.
Okay, all of the nations are on high
alert. Um, looks like the US was
planning a strike on Iran and then they
backed out backed out at the backed down
at the last minute.
I'd say that Saudi Arabia will
definitely be on high alert. So will be
Kuwait, UAE, Oman. Um Iraq for sure. Um
Turkey will be on high alert. Israel
will be on high alert. I suppose
Pakistan will go on high alert if the US
tells them to. And Bahrain is this
little little little nation here. Qatar
is on high alert for sure. They have
this aloud or whatever base there,
right? And Bahrain Bahrain also I
suppose would be on high alert.
everybody all all the nations in this
region right now because there's a
possibility of a US lead no action on
Iran.
Kiran Mores says why did the BJP have a
meeting meeting with the Chinese
Communist Party? Um I have not looked
into it. Has the BJP issued an official
statement as to why this meeting
happened? Look when the see the Chinese
Communist Party is a very major
political party. uh the political party
of China which is the most powerful
nation in Asia and we are the second
most powerful nation in Asia or largest
political party is the BJP. So when the
so I suppose there is some kind of
some kind of political activity
happening between the two countries
and the Chinese Communist Party
officials who came to India met with the
BJP leadership they also met with the
political leadership of other parties
okay it's not just the BJP understand
that so I'm not exactly sure why but
maybe it's a routine thing maybe there
is a chance of a rap between the two
countries potentially we'll see about
that too early to speculate
Dir Kamak says you say India is like
Nigeria yet India has nukes and fully
sovereign. Could you explain the
apparent contradiction? India is like
Nigeria with nukes in Nigeria with
sovereignty infrastructure trash.
Education garbage corruption allegedly
very high.
You see manufacturing what
manufacturing? What do we manufacture
that the world that we export to the
world? Don't say we export raw
materials, mangoes, bananas, all that.
We're not a banana republic, right? We
want to be a full manufacturing power.
Are we anything compared to China in
terms of manufacturing? No, we are
closer to Nigeria.
Living standards are closer to Nigeria
than to China. So it's like Nigeria with
nukes and full sovereignty. Same kind of
trash education system, comparable trash
living standards, infrastructure is
being built in India now. That's one
thing the government has done very well.
government the past 10 years but look at
the living standards quality of life in
the streets look at the pollution
right so I'm not saying that India
hasn't changed India has changed a lot
in the past 10 years but we are still I
mean look at the per capita GDP in India
and compare it with Nigeria okay let's
see
um one second
uh per capita GDP
India Nigeria
let's see
uh So India is 2.7 what? Okay. So India
is like two or three times that of
Nigeria but not like an order of
magnitude higher. So it it is a real
difference if it's an order of magnitude
higher. So you see overall India is like
that. India still got the GDP GD per
capita of overall similar to Africa
right that's what it is godliness says
what made Trump cancel the so-called
help he promised the Iranians also with
Chabahar gone we are are we fully
encircled P P P P P P P P P P P P P P P
P P P P PM was in Mara Lago. Oh, was he
in Mara Lago? Okay, are we fully
encircled? Not yet. Not quite fully
encircled. Chabahar essentially gone. uh
what made Trump cancel the so-called
healthy promise to the Iranians? I think
what I'm hearing is that the Saudis and
and the UAE said that you know what this
is not a good idea because we will
suffer as a consequence. If the
Americans attack Iran, Iran will attack
all the American bases in the region and
all the oil refineries in the region. Of
course they will. Of course they will.
Right? So Saudi Arabia will suffer.
Doesn't make sense for them to suffer
like that. And maybe they were able to
convince the Americans. Are we fully
encircled? Not quite. But we are getting
there. We are getting there. East
Pakistan gone. West Pakistan gone. Nepal
gone. Bhutan. Bhutan can be bought out
easily by the Americans. No question
about that. So we'll see. Maybe fully
encircled soon. It is what it is. That's
how it goes.
Died in plane crash. says many on
Russian social media alleged that Shyigu
turned the defense ministry into his
personal haram as a lot of young women
without any
mile XP were given positions even
trolling using terms like reindeer
herders haram okay I have absolutely no
idea about this
I have absolutely no idea I I don't
think Mr. Putin would tolerate anything
like this actually. So I I'm not aware
of this. Sorry. Okay. Smith Sarkcar.
Well, thank you very much Smithcar.
Thank you very much. And Smith again.
Thank you very much again.
Okay. Smithar says India's persistent
internal divisions and weak state
cohesion.
Is it time to acknowledge that
secularism and liberal democracy are
unsuitable for us? Absolutely 100%.
But what can we do about it? Because the
the folks who come to power through
secularism and democracy, they will not
give up power. They will never change
the system.
You see this
secularism and democracy were brought
into India as solutions to the alleged
problems that we had in India at the
time of independence and partition.
Right?
So what happened is that the folks to
whom trans the British transferred power
they put in place a permanent solution
for a temporary problem.
A permanent solution to a temporary
problem becomes a permanent problem.
This is what we are seeing now. India's
democracy is is further widening the
divisions the British have created.
Right? These divisions are artificial.
They were created by the British. And
today's politicians are exploiting these
divisions to play politics and get
votes. And they are further widening the
divisions
and weak state cohesion, too much
federalism, too weak of a central
government. Overall, democracy is a has
been a disaster for India. Disaster.
and pandering to the majority
to the to the lowest common denominator
that sort of thing. Uh it's been an
absolute disaster. It's it's it's
causing
a gradual
consistent lowering of Indian stand of
India standards. Not the standards
aren't being raised, they are being
lowered.
Rohil says besides the obvious global
powers like India first, China, Russia
and the US, it should be Russia. It
should be US, Russia, China, then India.
U okay but despite the these besides
these obvious global powers, do you
think there's a country silently rising
that could become a future superpower?
We not noticing see you have listed
four, right? India, China, Russia and
the US. Out of these four,
only three can potentially one is
already a superpower, the US. Only China
and Russia are in competition to perhaps
someday be a superpower. India is not in
the competition for being a superpower
right now.
Okay? And there is no country silently
rising that can be a future superpower
someday. I don't see any India is not in
the in the race for being superpower.
Okay? Please understand this.
Okay. CVS 2K says sun party. Sun party.
All right. All right. Thank you for
being a member for a month. Thank you so
much. Sam the Gamer says, "What's your
favorite car, diesel or petrol?" My
favorite car is powered by antimatter.
No, I don't I don't have a favorite car.
Diesel, petrol, fossil fuels, very bad,
very naughty, very nasty. Electric or
antimatter? Even nuclear will work, but
nuclear reactors are too large.
Uh DTI Sharma, thank you very much, DTI
Sharma. Thank you indeed.
Uh Shivarallay says India opens monument
conservation to private agencies ending
ASI's exclusive control and is William
Dal Rimple a good author to read books
about Indian history. Uh India opens
monument conservation to private
agencies. Has that happened? Let us find
out. Um that would be great. I it would
be very welcome from my perspective.
India opens monu monument
conservation
to
private agencies.
Okay. In a significant policy shift, the
government of India has decided to open
the conservation of all of of centrally
protected monuments to empanled private
agencies, ending the ASI's exclusive
role in restoration work. I think that's
an interesting move and probably a good
move
as long as they are able to ensure that
these private agencies do a good job.
Not like the ASI is doing a stellar job
by any means, but okay. Okay. So,
interesting.
Is William Dal Rimple a good author to
read books about Indian history?
I am not a fan of William Dalle, the fat
Scotsman.
Yeah.
I nothing against him being fan or
whatever. But the point is I am not a
fan of the guy. Okay? He's no expert on
Indian history
and he takes sides in Indian politics
and whatn not. He should stay out of
Indian politics. I'm not a fan of his.
All I'll say is that I don't have I
haven't read read a single book of his.
So probably I'm not the right guy to
answer the question. My point is I'm not
a fan of the person
because he is biased against India. He
takes sides. He takes the side of the
left
in the Indian history scene. And when
you take the side of the Indian left
instead of being neutral and pro putting
forth information in a neutral perspect
from a neutral perspective then you are
on the side of those who have been for
decades distorting Indian history. And
of course, this is his business. So he
seeks to sell as many books as possible.
So he's put forth narratives like the
true narrative this time about the fact
that the silk silk road is a myth. It
was India that was trading with the
west, not China. But the west has
created this entire illusion of the silk
road being this great thing. It was
India that was the major trader with the
west, not China. It was India that was
the major economy, not China. So he has
written a book about the silk road. I
haven't read it. Um this time clearly
he's telling the truth but a lot of his
history is so I haven't read a single of
his book a single book of his so I can't
really say but not a fan of his
field strongman says I passed with minus
35 in my postgraduate exam I'm on my way
to do kidney donation kidney operation
can I get your blessings and full
support sir full support indeed passed
with minus 35 in the PG exam on my on
your way to do kidney operation. Aha
you're a doctor
you know you're a doctor you got minus
35 in the posture exam you're going to
do a kidney operation all the best full
support sir this is India this is new
India this is India
Bisha says have you kissed the ring
congrats on 950k well 950k it's been
like months and months and months at 948
949 now it's 950 all right thank you
ma'am have I kissed the ring I haven't
kissed any rings I do not kiss any rings
I am fully independent as is
all right. Okay. Died in plane crash
says Millex means military experience.
Okay. Military experience. Also, Shuiku
had no military experience. Also, the
new defense minister
Bilusov has fired all those useless
women from defense ministry. Okay. Well,
I'm not aware of what's going on inside
behind the scenes all the women and
whatnot. Looks like if this is true,
then Shroyu needs to has some answering
to do. Yeah, Shyigu has no had no
military experience. Okay, I haven't
looked into these details, but
interesting indeed.
Well, thank you for for bringing this to
my notice. I we'll do some digging into
this. And that brings me to the end of
today's question and answer session.
I've taken in as many of the Q&As's as
possible from
the comments and a bunch of super chats
as well. Uh RDRA says, "Great content."
Thank you very much indeed. Thank you
very much. Uh and I'll take one final
question by Aayush. Don't you feel
jealous about how powerful the US is
compared to other nations? The number of
facults it is unmatched is unmatched. It
kidnaps presidents without any thinking.
I'm very indeed very jealous indeed.
But what can I do? Yeah, what can I do?
I am indeed jealous. I wish my country
was like that. But my my country has
different standards or leaders of
different standards. So what can we say?
That's where we are. All right, people.
Thank you so much for being on the live
stream for all your questions. I look
forward to doing your Okay, there's one
more super chat. Um V4 Valor says
today's episode made me sad about India.
Well, you see I I wish I did not make
you sad about India but I will not lie
to you. I will tell you the truth. The
truth isn't always nice.
Yeah. But I am still optimistic about
India. I am hopeful that we will not go
down the road of becoming a vasal
despite the odds being stacked against
us. I think it's a 65 70% chance that in
the next 5 years we become a US vasal.
But I'm hopeful that the 30% chance
comes out on top. So I'm still
optimistic.
Yeah, let's all be optimistic. The odds
are against us now. The Americans are
way too powerful, way more powerful than
us. But let's hope that we
still
remain sovereign as a nation. So don't
be sad, work hard and hope for the best.
All right. So people, thank you so much
everybody and I look forward to talking
to you in tomorrow's live stream which
is going to be entirely live chat super
chat. Look forward to that. Until then
take care, keep learning, keep asking
questions and keep raising your
standards.